<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The popish proselyte the grand fanatick. Or an antidote against the poyson of Captain Robert Everard's Epistle to the several congregations of the non-conformists</title>
            <author>Harrison, Joseph.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1684</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 157 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 84 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A45678</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H900</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R216554</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99828281</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99828281</idno>
            <idno type="VID">32708</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A45678)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 32708)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1865:27)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The popish proselyte the grand fanatick. Or an antidote against the poyson of Captain Robert Everard's Epistle to the several congregations of the non-conformists</title>
                  <author>Harrison, Joseph.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 156 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Samuel Tidmarsh, at the Kings Head in Cornhill, next house to the Royal Exchange,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCLXXXIV. [1684]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By Joseph Harrison.</note>
                  <note>A reply to: Everard, Robert.  An epistle to the several congregations of the non-conformists.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Dr. Williams' Library, London.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Everard, Robert, fl. 1664. --  Epistle to the several congregations of the non-conformists.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Catholics --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:32708:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:32708:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE <hi>Popiſh Proſelyte</hi> THE GRAND FANATICK.</p>
            <p>OR AN ANTIDOTE AGAINST The Poyſon of Captain <hi>Robert Everard</hi>'s Epiſtle to the ſeveral Congregations of the Non-conformiſts.</p>
            <q>
               <p>And many other Signs and Wonders truly did Jeſus in the preſence of his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, which are not written in this Book: But theſe are written that ye might believe that Jeſus is the Chriſt, the Son of God, and that in believing you might have life through his name.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>John 20.30, 31.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Samuel Tidmarſh,</hi> at the <hi>Kings Head</hi> in <hi>Cornhill,</hi> next Houſe to the <hi>Royal Exchange.</hi> MDCLXXXIV.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:32708:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:32708:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>AN exact anſwering of the whole Epiſtle by Paragraphs, would have ſwelled my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended little Book in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a great Volume; nor did I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it needful: and that becauſe the Captain himſelf hath contracted the pith of all that is pertinent, into his ſixth reaſon againſt the Scriptures being a Rule; His Argument from Heaven for the
<pb facs="tcp:32708:3"/> Roman Church being Judge and Guide; and his ſix Queries ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed utterly deſtructive to, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together unanſwerable upon, the grounds of Proteſtants; and now all theſe be at large tranſcribed, examined, and ſolved: And yet leſt the leſs intelligent Reader ſhould ſtumble, or the Adverſary inſult; I have in an admonitory prefatory diſcourſe ſo far taken notice of all his moſtly ſeeming important concluſions and objections, as to make it apparent that they have nought elſe, ſave ignorance, inadvertency, ſelfiſhneſs, and ſtrong deluſion to ſupport, and give riſe unto them. Nor yet have I made it my only buſineſs to pull down (though that muſt needs be their great work that have to do with Babel-builders) but have all along aſcertained what I would or ſhould eſtabliſh, from ſuch common principles of Religion and Reaſon, as are aſſented to by Papiſts,
<pb facs="tcp:32708:3"/> Proteſtants, and the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſality at leaſt of Chriſtians. As for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viling, had not his own guilt put him on to caution againſt it, I ſhould never have thought of it; what is of perſonal concern is oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned by his own writings, cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtant to the matter under de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate, and all contained in one ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle Page; the whole is cloſed with a vindication of the Great Saint <hi>Auguſtin</hi> from favouring the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings of ſo grand an Apoſtate as <hi>Robert Everard.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Joſeph Harriſon.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:32708:4"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:32708:4"/>
            <head>An Anſwer to <hi>Robert Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rard</hi>'s Epiſtle to the ſeveral Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations of the Nonconfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts.</head>
            <p>I Shall at preſent ſuppoſe <hi>Robert Everard</hi> to be no Romiſh Jeſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ited Prieſt,<note place="margin">Pag. <hi>91.</hi>
               </note> but <hi>Quondam</hi> Captain to a Troop of Rebellious Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, and do conclude from his own Printed papers, attended with ſome obvious circumſtances, that four things did chiefly concur to the ſhipwrack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his Faith; <hi>Firſt,</hi> Ignorance. <hi>Secondly,</hi> Inadvertency, or Impru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Self-intereſt. <hi>Fourthly,</hi> A juſt judgment of God in ſending ſuch ſtrong deluſions, that they ſhould believe a lie.</p>
            <p>The mans ignorance appears, <hi>Firſt</hi> in that he cannot conſtrue, <hi>credo Sanctam Eccleſiam Catholicam,</hi> I believe the Being, but renders (as if he had read) <hi>credo Sanctae,</hi> &amp;c. I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:32708:5"/> the ſaying, of the Holy Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Church; ſets hence in the front of his Book, and urges all a-long, the Churches, and in the iſſue the Roman Churches pretended infallible declaration for the foundation of Faith. When yet the very Creed teacheth him</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> To confeſs, <hi>I believe in God the Father, in the Son, and in the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> as that which muſt neceſſarily forego and found his believing firſt that there is a Holy Catholick Church, as well as that there is a Communion of Saints; nor doth it give any more ground to conclude the one, than the other for to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible. <hi>Secondly,</hi> Though the Captain before the cloſure of the Book, be ſo well taught, as to prove the Roman Church infallible in teaching, from certain ſtories about Miracles no more than pointed at, out of <hi>Breer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leys</hi> Index, no more than ſurmiſed to be done by S. <hi>Francis,</hi> S. <hi>Dominick,</hi> and the Monk <hi>Auſtin,</hi> with ſuch like, to confirm, and that but ſome few of her ſuperſtitious Doctrins; Nay can chide ſuch, as Perſons deſtroying Faith,<note place="margin">Pag. <hi>78.</hi>
               </note> taking away all humane con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:32708:5"/> 
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that ſhall refuſe upon ſuch fallible Teſtimonies to believe ſtories ſo extreamly improbable; yet is he ſuch a Novice in the beginning, that he cannot ſo much as offer an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for the truth of Chriſtianity, from all the undoubted Miracles wrought by Chriſt and his Apoſtles,<note place="margin">Pag. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> for no other end ſave the confirming thereof, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.3, 4. recorded in Sacred Writ, that we might believe, <hi>John</hi> 20.31. not denyed by the Adverſaries of our Faith, and moſt celebriouſly atteſted by the unanimous conſent of all Chriſtians in all ſucceeding Ages. Nor has he a word to ſay to the Gentleman that in oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the Evangeliſt, calls Faith thus founded, an opinion, an humour: But inſtead of that, <hi>gratis</hi> grants, that unleſs we know what <hi>ex parte rei</hi> is impoſſible to be known, our ſelves or thoſe that teach us to be infallible, Chriſtianity as to us, can be no more than probably, not moſt probably true. <hi>Jews, Turks,</hi> and Pagans may be as well perſwaded of their ſeveral ways, as we can be of ours; both upon a fallible certainty: Not knowing ſure, that the Chriſtians
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:32708:6"/>
[certainty] hath no [fallible] ſave that they may; the <hi>Jews, Turks</hi> and <hi>Pagans</hi> [fallible] no [certainty] ſave that they do, <hi>imagine</hi> it.</p>
            <p>And <hi>ſecondly,</hi> that it is irrational thus to argue, <hi>à Doctore ad Doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam,</hi> from the Perſon to the thing, from what may be, to what is. <hi>Euclid</hi> may be fallible, and yet his demonſtrations not deceive; we may know our ſelves, and thoſe that teach us, to be ſubject to miſtake; and yet know too, that in this or that particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar neither they nor we are miſtaken.</p>
            <p>Chriſtianity as to us may be cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly true; certainly ſo demonſtrated to <hi>Jews, Turks</hi> and Pagans: and yet every Man confeſſed to be a liar, every Church <hi>ex parte ſui</hi> in a poſſibility to commit an error in this thing; But,</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3dly.</hi> The man cannot diſtinguiſh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the internal teſtimony of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit vouchſafed ſometimes unto ſome, and that conſtant hiſtorical evidence which is afforded unto all. When he was a <hi>Quaker,</hi> it's like he confounded the original Cauſe, and the original Language, and now he cannot make a difference betwixt the efficient cauſe of our believing, and the formal ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:32708:6"/> ground or Reaſon of Faith. He diſcourſes with a man ſenſual, as if he had the ſpirit; and imagines, that the Holy Ghoſt, which is ſent to witneſs with our ſpirits that we are the children of God, ſhould in the ſame manner and meaſure, witneſs the Divine truth of every particular Book and Text of Scripture. And hence inſtead of Firſtly telling the ſenſual Lay Gentleman, that he believed the Scriptures to be the word of God <hi>fide Hiſtorica,</hi> by an Hiſtorical Faith, upon the account of univerſal Tradition; He talks with him about an inward infallible Teſtimony of the Spirit, and makes that ſpiritual ſenſe and feeling, which is peculiar to Gods Elect ſealing up their intereſt in Chriſt, to be the common convincing ground of that being indeed the Spirits Teſtimony. And whereas he ſhould have reſolved his faith into the Sovereign Authority, and verity of God himſelf ſpeaking in Scriptures as the formal ground thereof, and into the ſpirits inlightning, inlivening Power as the efficient cauſe; He reſolves it wholly into an inward Teſtimony of the ſpirit, of which,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:32708:7"/> (for ought appears) neither of the twain (ſave by hear-ſay) knew any thing at all. However inſtead of the Spirits teſtimony, the man might better have ſaid in this caſe, ſimply by the Spirit; by the Spirit <hi>(ſcilicet)</hi> as that <hi>medium facultatis</hi> whereby we are enabled to ſee and believe ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural verities to be Divine. Albeit, as Dr. <hi>Ames</hi> well obſerveth,<note place="margin">Medull. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> there is a ſufficient and certain repreſentation propoſed to us in the Scripture, both of things that are to be believed; and of that Reaſon upon which we ought to believe them. See <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.26. Nor yet,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Does he perceive the difference betwixt faith Dogmatical complex, aſſenting to the truth of Divine propoſitions, and that faith which we call ſalvifical, incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plex, fixing on, adhering to, and reſting in Jeſus Chriſt alone? That may be various, reſpect had to its object; the ſame man knows ſuch a propoſition to be revealed to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, which he knows not to day; and conſequently, believe that to morrow, which to day he does not. This, reſpect had to the object, varies
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:32708:7"/> not: It's <hi>Jeſus, the ſame Yeſterday, to Day, and for ever.</hi> Though yet reſpect had to the ſubject like as the other, it's ſometimes weaker or ſtronger, confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, or more diſtinct. And hence men of different faiths incomplex cannot be ſaved; <hi>for there is no other name under Heaven given,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Acts</hi> 4.12. <hi>other foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation can no man lay, than that is laid, which is Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.11. oneneſs of Faith, as to this, is commended and commanded, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.5. compared with <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.13. <hi>unto the unity of the Faith and knowledge of the Son of God. He that believeth on the Son of God, hath life Eternal; and he that believeth not,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>John</hi> 3.36. But men may be of different faiths complex, believe diverſe, nay contrary propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions, and yet through Grace obtain ſalvation. Some build Gold, Silver, precious Stones; ſome Wood, Hay, Stubble; <hi>one believeth he may eat all things, another who is weak, eateth Herbs,</hi> Rom. 14.2.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly</hi> and Laſtly, the man ſeems not to know of any difference betwixt an acquired Habit and a Divine Gift, the requiſites to our getting of Science, and Gods giving of Faith. Science, it's
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:32708:8"/> true (as <hi>Thomas</hi> determines) cannot be had, unleſs we firſt know the certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the <hi>Medium,</hi> or Reaſon where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the concluſion is demonſtrated; but it is impertinent to Faith, as <hi>Eſtius</hi> well concludes, by what means we believe the prime Verity, that is, by what means God uſeth to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow on men the gift of Faith. He may do it as well by the preaching of the meaneſt Miniſter, as of the greateſt Apoſtle: for indeed neither the one nor the other is or needs to be (what he ſuppoſes) a foundation or Argument whereon to build, but ſimply a <hi>medium</hi> or inſtrument whereby is begotten and brought forth that Faith which is of the ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of God.<note place="margin">Page <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> And therefore in vain does he diſpute about the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Chriſtians believing, either becauſe the Apoſtles ſo taught, or <hi>Simon Magus</hi> ſo affirmed; for it was not becauſe, but by the Preaching, whether of <hi>Paul,</hi> or <hi>Apollos,</hi> that they did believe; <hi>We have not do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion over your Faith,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.24. <hi>Who then is Paul? or who is Apollos? but Miniſters by whom ye believed, even as the Lord gave to every man,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.5.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:32708:8"/>
            <p>The Captains inadvertency, or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prudence is as evident</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> In that he never calls to mind, that Prieſts and Jeſuites paſs uſually under the Notion of Lay Gentlemen, and great Folks Couſins: Truſts, <hi>Eve</hi> like, to his own skill, and never makes known either his doubts, or the Gentlemans objections to any of the Proteſtant Miniſters. He borrows, it's true, a certain deal of Popiſh Books; <hi>The Queſtion of Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions, Novelty repreſſed, Fiat Lux, Infidelity unmasked, or a confutation of a Book publiſhed by Mr.</hi> William Chillingworth, but never inquires for Mr. <hi>William Chillingworth</hi>'s own Book, nor Dr. <hi>Hammonds</hi> anſwer to <hi>Infidelity <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nmasked,</hi> in his vindication of the Lord <hi>Falkland.</hi> He never ſends to Dr. <hi>Owen</hi> for his animadverſions on <hi>Fiat Lux,</hi> nor adviſeth with Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> about <hi>Novelty ſuppreſt:</hi> Had he conſulted with theſe Miniſters of ours, and told us wherein they failed in the anſwering either theſe Books, or the Lay Gentlemans Objections, it might have been of ſome moment, have ſtartled perhaps ſome of the Nonconformiſts; but to make a
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:32708:9"/> ſtirr and a ſtory, how mildly, how profoundly the Lay Gentleman ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected; and then how extreamly trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, how ſtrangely the Horſe-Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain was gravelled, argues nothing, ſave the Gentlemans cunning crafti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and the Captains daſtardly weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: the cauſe no more concerned, than if they had never had meeting.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> He never conſidered that the Gentleman was altogether for asking queſtions, <hi>Robert</hi> never pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes any; for if, when the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain was gravelled, and could not cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly prove the truth of Chriſtianity from his own Fanatick Principles, he had put the Gentleman to it to have proved Chriſtianity certainly true from the Popiſh, a hundred to one, but they had both proved Heathens; the one being no more able to eſtabliſh it by Miracles upon the infallibility of the Roman Church, than the other by ſenſe and feeling upon the Spirits Teſtimony: the man now knows and finds this to be true enough; and therefore in the conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion doth he preſent us with ſix que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, conjures his old Brethren to anſwer them, and withal, warily pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vides
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:32708:9"/> that they ſhall not ask him any queſtion at all; but firſt aſcertain what they would eſtabliſh: for ſays he <hi>Page</hi> 85. <hi>Who knows not, if a Man will give himſelf ſcope to be bold, he may raiſe Arguments againſt the belief of the Trinity, or any other Myſtery of Faith, that will puzzle learned Men to anſwer; a piece of cunning and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, I could wiſh all our weaker ſort of Proteſtants to take ſpecial notice of.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> The man unadviſedly all along confounds endeavours to fix, and find in the ſame ſubject, the Rule, Judge and Guide of Faith; when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as theſe three are in their reſpective Natures, Uſes, Ends diſtinct, and ſcarcely poſſible to be ſubjected in the ſame thing or perſon: The Scripture may be a Rule certain and ſtable as <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> and yet no Judge. Reaſon may be a judge, or rather that whereby every man is to judge for himſelf, as <hi>Chillingworth,</hi> and yet no Rule. The ſpirit may be Guide, to direct, draw and lead us into all truth, and yet neither rule nor judge, The Church by her Miniſtry may be ſubſervient to the ſpirit in leading, helpful to us in finding out, applying
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:32708:10"/> of, and judging according to the Rule, and yet the Church it ſelf be neither Rule, Judge, nor Guide; nor will now that grand Sophiſm [the Spirit is not, Reaſon is not, the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture is not, the Judge, Rule and Guide, and therefore the Church is] be of any force: for never to take notice, that it founds an affirmative concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on upon negative premiſſes; it ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes that ſome Presbyterians, Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendents, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſhould hold, the Spirit alone, ſome Reaſon, ſome the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, each excluſive of the Miniſtry of the Church, to be the Rule, Judge, and Guide of Faith; whenas all they joyntly, in this buſineſs, joyn all theſe together, and look up unto God, according to his command and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, for his Holy ſpirit in the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es Miniſtery, throughly to direct their underſtandings in judging of things according to the written Rule.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> The man never perceives that his own vain ratiocinations and needleſs conceſſions are the ſole ground that is given for him to bottom his belief upon; a ſtrong fancy he has, and need on, for his Faith's no ſtronger. To evince this I
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:32708:10"/> ſhall inſtance in theſe ſix poſitions laid down and ſuppoſed as the Baſis of his whole diſcourſe. <hi>Firſt,</hi> Faith is an infallible aſſent of the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, ſubmitting it ſelf obediently to believe the Revelations of God. <hi>Secondly,</hi> There muſt be ſome means appointed of God, by which we may know this one true Faith from all falſe opinions. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Theſe means muſt be infallible. <hi>Fourthly,</hi> The underſtanding muſt ſubmit to theſe means under pain of Damnation. <hi>Fifthly,</hi> Two men of two different faiths or beliefs cannot be ſaved. <hi>Sixthly,</hi> Ignorant people by ſuch rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable diligence as is very tolerable to Humane frailty, and yet poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for them, may come to the knowledge (wiſely done to leave out <hi>certain</hi>) of theſe means. And now if you ask what foundation he has whereupon to ground his belief of theſe aſſertions, he'll tell you, I ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered them from the true interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of certain Texts of Scripture.<note place="margin">Pag. <hi>16.</hi>
               </note> And if you ask further, how he knows that interpretation to be true? Has he Divine Revelation for it? Accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the tenour of his own firſt
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:32708:11"/> poſition: Has he the unanimous conſent of the Fathers for it? Or does he certainly know, beyond all poſſibility of being miſtaken, that the Church in all Ages hath, and the preſent Church now doth give that interpretation accordingly as 'tis decreed by the Council of <hi>Trent?</hi> No, but from hence I thought (ſays he) it did very naturally follow: Firſtly,<note place="margin">17.</note> Secondly, and Thirdly, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And yet that it may appear, he only ſays, could not poſſibly think, any ſuch a thing, obſerve from that exhortation, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.23. <hi>Let us hold faſt the profeſſion of our Hope</hi> (ſo in their own Authentick Tranſlation) <hi>undeclining,</hi> does he inferr, Faith is an infallible aſſent of our underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: and becauſe the latter part of the verſe, <hi>for he is faithful that hath promiſed,</hi> founded the confidence, there ſpoken of, upon the promiſe of Grace; and the former Verſe fixed faith with its full aſſurance upon the High Prieſt Jeſus alone; The man ſlily paſſeth over both, and leaves the other part of his propoſition (<hi>obediently ſubmitting,</hi> &amp;c.) deſtitute of any proof. From 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.5. <hi>bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:32708:11"/> into Captivity every thought to the Obedience of Chriſt;</hi> he infers, the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding muſt ſubmit, not diſpute: all be Damned that diſobey the Authority of the Church; and adds withal, that ſaving faith is ſeated in the underſtanding, as if <hi>Paul</hi> had been miſtaken when he ſaid, <hi>with the heart man believeth unto Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> Rom. 10.10. or as if he himſelf knew not what he had done in putting <hi>[obediently ſubmitting]</hi> into the defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of faith, ſith all conclude, obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and diſobedience to be ſubjected in the will. From <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.5. <hi>there is but one Faith,</hi> reſpect had to the perſonal object in whom, the Lord Jeſus; He concludes, that two men of dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering faiths Dogmatical, or that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve two contrary opinions cannot be ſaved; nor is he aſhamed, from <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 35.8. plainly pointing at Chriſt, the new and living way, firſt to take out, <hi>and the unclean ſhall not paſs over it,</hi> as incoherent, becauſe their unholy Mother admits of ſuch for her children; and then inferrs, that ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant people by reaſonable diligence, may come to the knowledge of thoſe means, about which yet their learned
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:32708:12"/> men to this very day could never be agreed. Nor can he himſelf tell, when it comes to the pinch, how thoſe means ſhould be certainly manifeſt, ſave by miracles, of which we ignorant folk may often hear, but never come to the knowledge of: however, that I moſt admire at, is, That the man deſigning to prove, that true acceptable faith con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts in believing as the Church be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves, a believing that the Roman Church is infallible, ſhould quote <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.6. that holds out the faith, <hi>without which it is impoſſible to pleaſe God,</hi> to be a believing; not that the Church, but that God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf is ſo: <hi>he that comes to God, muſt believe that he is,</hi> &amp;c. And further, that he ſhould ſtand hafling and pafling, and proving by halfs, there muſt be ſome means appointed by God, by which men may know, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> thoſe means muſt be infallible, the underſtanding muſt ſubmit to thoſe means under pain of damnation; when the very Text quoted, <hi>Mark.</hi> 16.16. ſhews plainly, that there be means, infallible means, and which be the means appointed,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:32708:12"/> whereby true faith both is begotten, and may be known from all falſe opinions, and unto which all that heartily ſubmit ſhall be ſaved, and thoſe that do not, ſhall be damned: and leſt you ſhould miſtake in read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the means be, the word of truth, the Goſpel Preached though by the mouth of never ſo weak a Miniſter. <hi>Go into all the World, and Preach the Goſpel unto every Creature; He that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveth and is Baptized ſhall be ſaved, and he that believeth not ſhall be dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned:</hi>
               <note place="margin">A Genere ad ſpeciem affirmat. non valet Argumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum.</note> nor yet is it unworthy of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark, 1. That means in general is here all along found in the premiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and Authority in ſpeciall put after into the concluſion: there muſt be, there is an infallible Means, and therefore there is, there muſt be an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible Authority. And 2. That the man ſeriouſly endeavours to found the very foundation of his own faith upon Scriptures, dark Scriptures privately interpreted, howbeit the main ſcope of his Book is to evince that faith, true faith, neither firſt nor laſt, can or ought to be founded there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:32708:13"/>
            <p>That ſelf-intereſt had a hand in the Captains overturning, ſeems more than probable;<note place="margin">Pag. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> becauſe, Firſt, The Captain in the late Wars (as his Book relates) had run through the ſeveral forms of Religion, <hi>Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terian, Independent, Anabaptiſt,</hi> &amp;c. and yet never, that we read of, loſt his preferment upon any Turn, nor miſſed of it for want of timely turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; and ſith ſo, the man might ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily foreſee, that ſuch a notorious Jugler was never like to be truſted at the Kings Court: Beſt for him now at laſt to turn Papiſt, do the Jeſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>its ſome ſignal ſervice, declare againſt his old friends, and their old ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, the Nonconformiſts, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps by that wile he might in the Queens Chapel come in time to get advancement. For,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> If ſeditions, Schiſms, He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies amongſt Proteſtants, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes with Lay-Gentlemen in their quarters could have overturned the faith of Captains, never ſo like to have been done as during the late diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions; but for all that while, though we heard of ſome Popiſh Champions turning Sectaries, yet of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:32708:13"/> no Sectarian Captain that became a Romaniſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> The mans carriage all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long makes manifeſt, that the ſelfiſh wiſdom of the Old wily Serpent is yet remaining with him: he knows well enough that there's nothing more inconſiſtent with Papal govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment than the Oaths of Allegiance and Supremacy; nor any thing more oppoſite to Popiſh Doctrine, than the 39 Ariticles: and yet can he neither be content to ſay ill, nor ſay nothing of our Engliſh Epiſcopacy; but upon occaſion is bowing down himſelf un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it, in the days of yore; doubtleſs he got to be a Captain by praying and preaching like ſome ſort of a Saint, and now time after time, is crying up himſelf for a good Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, leaves the Epiſcopal Church out of his Catalogue of Sects, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends a great deal of Reverence to any profeſſion that ſhall be eſtabliſhed by Law.</p>
            <p>But above all, the juſt judgment of God is moſt remarkable in ſending him and ſuch like, ſtrong deluſion, <hi>that they ſhould believe a lie,</hi> and that <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they received not the love of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:32708:14"/> the truth, that they might be ſaved, but had pleaſure in unrighteouſneſs:</hi> nor need I divine the no love this man had to the truth; and the great pleaſure he always had and now hath in unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs is notoriouſly manifeſt by his Firſt, Blaſpheming the Spirit; Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, Abuſing Reaſon; Thirdly, Vilifying the Scriptures; Fourthly, Wronging the Church Catholick; Fifthly, Belying Proteſtants; Sixthly, Diſſembling the Tenets of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts.</p>
            <p>The ſpirit is blaſphemed, 1. by giving that glory of Infallibility, which is peculiar to the Holy Ghoſt, to the organs or inſtruments by which he is pleaſed to reveal the mind of God. Men ſpeaking from delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration uſe free-will, may ſpeak or not ſpeak, ſpeak truth or falſhood, and conſequently for that time can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but be fallible. And when men ſpeak divinely, yet not deliberately, it is not properly they that ſpeak, but the Holy Ghoſt that ſpeaketh in them. <hi>The word of the Lord came to me, ſaying. The mouth of the Lord hath ſpoken it.</hi> And in this caſe 'tis the word ſpoken that is infallible, and not they that
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:32708:14"/> ſpeak it. It were not proper for ſuch on that account to ſay, <hi>It ſeemeth good to the Holy Ghoſt, and to us;</hi> but, not we, but the Holy Ghoſt, <hi>not I, but the Lord:</hi> and hence the eternal God is ſaid internally to demonſtrate by his ſpirit, and externally to confirm by miracles, not the infallibility of the organ through which he ſpeaks, but the infallible truth of the word that is ſpoken. <hi>And they went forth every where, the Lord working with them, and confirming the word with ſigns following,</hi> Mark 16.20.2. The ſpirit expreſly, 1 <hi>John</hi> 4.2, 3. makes the Doctrine Preached the Rule, according to which we are to try the ſpirits; <hi>Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by know we the ſpirit of God: Every ſpirit that confeſſeth that Jeſus Chriſt is come in the fleſh, is of God: and every ſpirit that confeſſeth not,</hi> &amp;c. And yet does the man wittingly conceal that, and wreſts verſe 6. to the making of the hearing of the Apoſtle, the only rule of trying of ſpirits, without regard had to their Doctrine. Nor does he <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> here, but ſuppoſing <hi>[we]</hi> verſe 6. to denote the ſame perſons as <hi>[ye]</hi> verſe 4. confidently concludes, hearing of Chriſts Apoſtles then was,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:32708:15"/> therefore hearing Popiſh Prieſts now is, the only rule. The Apoſtle doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs ſaw this myſtery of iniquity be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning then to work; and therefore leaves us a general Rule without any exception. 2 <hi>Joh.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Whoſoever tranſgreſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth and abideth not in the doctrine of Chriſt, hath not God. He that abideth in the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Chriſt, he hath the Father and the Son. If there come any to you, and bringeth not this doctrine, receive him not into the Houſe, neither bid him God ſpeed.</hi> 3. The man reviles the Saints, that have received the Holy anoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, tells how they would have the world believe that they have the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, without bringing Reaſon, Evidence, Teſtimony or Authority to evince it: whenas yet if either Reaſon, Evidence, Teſtimony, or Authority may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded, <hi>the Tree is known by its fruits,</hi> and their having the ſpirit, manifeſt by <hi>Love, Joy, Peace, Long-ſuffering, Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Goodneſs, Faith, Meekneſs, Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance.</hi> Gal. 5.22. They confeſs that <hi>Jeſus is come in the Fleſh,</hi> as aforeſaid, and, <hi>that Jeſus is the Lord,</hi> which no man <hi>can, but by the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.3. Nor need he trouble himſelf with telling,<note place="margin">Page <hi>21.</hi>
               </note> that if it be the ſpirit
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:32708:15"/> of God they have, he is infallible in his teaching, and both they and all the world are obliged under pain of Damnation to believe what he deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers as matter of faith, to be true. For 1. Though they ſay they have the ſpirit of God, and that he is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible in his teaching, yet they do not ſay, Pope-like, that they are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by made infallible in theirs. He teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth all of them the whole truth as it is in Jeſus, <hi>for they ſhall all know me from the leaſt of them to the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt of them, ſaith the Lord,</hi> Jer. 31.34. but teaches not any, all the points of Doctrine that be true, <hi>for we know in part, and propheſie in part,</hi> 1 Cor. 13.9. <hi>according to the meaſure of the gift of Chriſt,</hi> Eph. 4.7.2. Both they and all the world are obliged under pain of Damnation to believe whatſoever God ſays is true, and ſo many as know that there is an Holy Ghoſt, are obliged in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner to believe whatſoever ſhall be delivered by that promiſed ſpirit of truth. But as to the particulars he ſhall deliver, the caſe is different. The Saints are ſeverally bound to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve whatſoever he ſhall convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:32708:16"/> deliver to any of them; and the world bound to believe what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever he ſhall convincingly deliver to the World: <hi>when he comes he ſhall convince,</hi> Joh. 16.8. Nor yet, 3. do they look (as ſome would ſeem to ſuppoſe) that others ſhould believe what they ſay, to be true, either becauſe they ſay or prove that they have the Spirit, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Adoption or Prophecy, but becauſe when and ſo far as that ſame Spirit by undeniable reaſons and teſtimonies ſhall make manifeſt in their conſciences the truth of what they do aſſert: <hi>by the manifeſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the truth, commending our ſelves to every mans conſcience in the ſight of God,</hi> 2 Cor. 4.2.</p>
            <p>Reaſon is a means whereby we come to know what is, not, what ought to be revealed; a means whereby we judge of things Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine according to the Rule, though yet it be not, may not be called the Rule according to which we are to judge: Reaſon I ſay that is thus uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and ought to be thus limited, the man one while enſlaves, and then anon ſets it up for an abſolute
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:32708:16"/> Lord. When reaſon comes to argue againſt the Churches Infallibility, then muſt it Vaſſal-like ſubmit, not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute, not wait for an effectual con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction according to Chriſts promiſe and procedure, <hi>And when he is come, he ſhall convince,</hi> &amp;c. but yield forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with to what the Church ſays; nay, to whatſoever an ignorant Engliſh Romiſh Prieſt can have the confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to ſay, their Church hath ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently propoſed; or if Reaſon offer to produce arguments to prove the truth of Chriſtianity, and evince the Scripture to be the word of God, urge Miracles, Univerſal-Tradition, conclude from Topicks internal, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal, in other caſes cogent and demonſtrative, yet then Reaſon is fallible, ſubject to error, a private ſpirit, a fancy, can make things at beſt appear no more than probable; <hi>Jews, Turks</hi> and <hi>Pagans</hi> may be as fully perſwaded, and upon as good rational grounds of the truth of their Religion, as we can of ours. But now if reaſon will be corrupted, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come an Advocate for <hi>Rome,</hi> her very ſophiſms ſhall be cryed up as ſufficient grounds for us to found our faith
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:32708:17"/> upon. God will not be defective in neceſſaries, and therefore there muſt be an infallible, viſible Judge. Chriſt is the only abſolute, inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent head of the Church, but may, and therefore hath appointed a dependent head derived from him. It is moſt rational in buſineſs of civil concernment, to rely on a Council of wiſe and learned men: And therefore in things ſpiritual, which God uſually hides from the wiſe and prudent, and the natural man receives not, we ought to rely on a Council of Popiſh Prelates. The Eunuch could not underſtand the Prophecy of <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> till miniſterially expounded by <hi>Philip</hi> the Deacon: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore cannot we underſtand that Text though already expounded, no nor any other till Authoritatively inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preted by the Roman Church. The Apoſtles, Elders, and Brethren when ſent to, ſent out a Tempora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Decree about things indifferent, made then by circumſtances in ſome places antecedently neceſſary, bind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing only in thoſe places, and preſſed with an <hi>[if]</hi> ye do theſe things, ye do well. And therefore the Cardinals,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:32708:17"/> Biſhops and Abbots may and ought to frame an everlaſting Law about points of Doctrine, make that neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary for all men, which God never made neceſſary for any, and preſs it under the dread of an Anathema, or pain of Eternal damnation: Nay, though God ſay, <hi>to the Law and to the Teſtimony, the Law of the Lord is perfect, the Scripture able not only to make wiſe to Salvation,</hi> but ſo far profitable, <hi>that the man of God,</hi> the Paſtor, <hi>may be throughly furniſhed unto every good work;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hominem Dei vocat Doctorem &amp; Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pum, ut dixi <hi>Ep. 1. C. 6. ver. 11. Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel.</hi> à Lapid.</note> yet it Reaſon can find any thing to ſay againſt the Scripture's being a Rule, it ſhall be heard. The Scripture then muſt not be a Rule, and why? Has God any where contradicted himſelf, and ſaid it muſt not? Has he any where appointed another? No, but here's a firſt rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and a ſecond reaſon, and a third reaſon, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and therefore it muſt be none, and yet the ſum of all no more than this; Some Chriſtians are dim-ſighted, ſome perverſe; many are carnal, walk as men, will not be ruled; and therefore the Scripture is not the Rule, Ruler ſure he would have ſaid; ſome people are contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:32708:18"/> Lawyers, corrupt, and differ in their opinions, and therefore the Law of the Land is not what it is; <hi>ſcilicet,</hi> the Law of the Land ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to which controverſies may and ought to be decided: and now</p>
            <p>The Church, before, under, and ſince the Law, will ſhe, nill ſhe, muſt always have been, and for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be, this Rule; when as yet it is evident that the Word was a rule both to <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> before the Church had Being, <hi>it ſhall bruiſe thy head,</hi> Geneſ. 3.15. God ſaid to <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham, ſo ſhall thy ſeed be; and he believed in the Lord,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Gen.</hi> 15.5, 6. <hi>Nor was it written for his ſake alone, but for us alſo,</hi> Rom. 4.23, 24. <hi>Ye ſhall not add to the word I command you, neither ſhall ye diminiſh ought from it,</hi> was given in charge to the Church of the <hi>Jews,</hi> Deut. 4.2. <hi>And if any man</hi> (ſays the Apoſtle) <hi>Preach unto you any other Goſpel than that ye have received, let him be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed,</hi> Gal. 1.9. <hi>Theſe are written, that ye might believe that Jeſus is the Chriſt the Son of God, and that believing ye might have life through his name,</hi> Joh. 20.31.
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:32708:18"/> Nor yet is it the queſtion, whether the Scripture accidentally taken, or the Word as written; but whether the Scripture taken Eſſentially, or the mind of God communicated at ſundry times, and in divers manners to and by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, Preached by the Apoſtles,<note place="margin">Non enim per alios diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem ſalutis cognovimus, quàm per eos per quos Evangelium pervenit ad nos, quod quidem tunc praeconiaverunt; poſtremò ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rò per Dei voluntatem in Scripturis nobis tradiderunt fundamentum &amp; columnam fidei noſtrae futurum nobis. <hi>Iren. I. 3.</hi> c. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> and now committed and conveyed down to us by Sacred writing, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways hath, is, &amp; ought to be owned for the rule of Faith: or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther indeed (becauſe it ſeems you long to have the queſtion ſtated with that advantage) even in <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brahams</hi> and the Apoſtles times, others as well as <hi>Sarah,</hi> Gen. 21.10. and the <hi>Beraeans,</hi> Act. 17.11. might not have urged, demanded, and without the juſt controul of any then viſible authority, have believed and acted according to the preſcript of that Rule, your own inſtances, <hi>Page</hi> 53. of extraordinary actions done, and Commands given by Gods directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, by the mouths of ſeveral par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:32708:19"/> Prophets, ſubmitted to (as you ſay) without further enquiry, do plainly evince as much, and alſo intimate that the will or word of God, which way ſoever it be made known, whether immediately or mediately; whether by Prophecy, Tradition or Writing, is and always has been the ſupream Rule both of Faith and Practice; and its adequation, as to matters of Faith, as now con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in, and expreſſed by the Scripture,<note place="margin">Sure foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. <hi>page</hi> 18. 20.</note> ſhall be after cleared. However the Church (as your own <hi>J. S.</hi> well obſerves) being a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation of the faithful, muſt needs preſuppoſe the notion of faithful, faithful, the notion of Faith, Faith, of the rule of Faith, an evident ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument that the Church is and ought to be regulated in believing; and conſequently ſhe her ſelf cannot be the rule of belief, nor any more, ſave as the ſame man ſays of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, Doctors, and great Scholars, and might as well have ſaid the ſame of Tradition too, a means to bring others to the knowledge of it. But,</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:32708:19"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> The man will needs ſeat authority in the Holy Catholick Church, notwithſtanding that autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity Supream, Magiſterial, formal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as well as radically is ſeated in Chriſt. <hi>All authority is given to me,</hi> Matt. 28.18. Nor is the Church the ſubject, but the object of the Miniſterial Power, <hi>He gave ſome Apoſtles, ſome Paſtors, for the perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting of the Saints, for the work of the Miniſtery, for the edification of the body of Chriſt,</hi> Eph. 4.11, 12. God hath ſet ſome in the Church, Firſt, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.18. and by the way, [ſome] in the Church, not [one over] the Church; for the whole, reſpect had to its organical frame, form, or Government, is divided into ſeveral Churches, ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Congregations, if you will, as well as the world into ſeveral King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms. <hi>To the angel of the Church of Epheſus,</hi> Rev. 2.1. <hi>We have no ſuch cuſtom, neither the Churches of God,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.16. Nor did <hi>Paul</hi> treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. concerning ſpiritual gifts, relate to a chief in governing, but the choiceſt for Propheſying,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:32708:20"/> when he ſaid, <hi>nor again, the Head to the Feet, I have no need of you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Although the Biſhops of <hi>Rome,</hi> in that very thing (as <hi>Gregory</hi> well notes) forerunners of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, did frequently challenge an Univerſal Juriſdiction; yet was it never owned, nor ſubmitted to by the Catholick Church, as it is evident from S. <hi>Cyprian,</hi> oppoſing <hi>Stephanus, Irenaeus</hi> reproving of <hi>Victor, Jerom</hi>'s <hi>Eugubium,</hi> and the ſixth Council of <hi>Carthage,</hi> in which was <hi>Auguſtin,</hi> and <hi>Aurelius;</hi> as alſo from the Acts of three of the four firſt General Councils, <hi>Nice, Conſtantinople</hi> and <hi>Chalcedon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> The man in the Cloſe, reſtrains the Church Catholick to a Church of one denomination cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Roman, meaning though thereby, not what <hi>Paul</hi> meant, <hi>the Saints at Rome,</hi> Rom. 1.7. but all that vaſtly extended community of Chriſtians which live in communion with, and in ſubjection to, the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> as to their ſupream Paſtor, and Governour on Earth in all things appertaining unto faith, next under
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:32708:20"/> Chriſt, when as yet the Arguments, and Texts all along produced ſeemingly militate for the infallibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of the Church; not this or that Church though never ſo vaſtly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended; and above all, not for the old Roman (and therefore he did wiſely to frame a new one) for it's expreſly declared fallible, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.22. And yet again, <hi>pag.</hi> 61. we are preſented with a General Council of Prelates as this Church, this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible Rule, which can by no means be identified with all that vaſtly extended community, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And yet let him take which he will, he'l be ſtill at a loſs. For ſuch an Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly of Prelates is not now in being, nor like to be, nor has there been any ſuch for a Century of years laſt paſt: And as for all the Chriſtians of that vaſt community, they are to be judged, ruled, guided, and conſequently not the Rule, Judge and Guide: If exempted from error perſonal, it were well. Judicial infallibility concerns not them. In the beginning he's for ſubmiſſion to the Holy Catholick Church, and now as if by [Holy Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church] he did not mean the
<pb facs="tcp:32708:21"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:32708:21"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:32708:22"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:32708:22"/>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:32708:23"/> Holy Catholick Church his Mother, nor any thing elſe ſave the Pope his Father, he's for ſubmiſſion and obedience to the Biſhop of <hi>Rome.</hi> The matter and marvel is, that the man has been tewing and tugging and troubling himſelf and us all this while, about an univerſal infallible viſible Authoritative Church, and now in the iſſue can neither tell, who, where, or what it is. However ſith the Church is ſuch an one, which is truly appointed by God to be this infallible Judge, muſt needs (as he ſaith) have this condition,<note place="margin">Pag. <hi>72.</hi>
               </note> that ſhe doth own her infallibility; It is incumbent upon the Captain in the firſt place to make it out, that the preſent Roman viſible Church doth plainly own her infallibility, (for his owning, and inferences we ſhall not regard,) or elſe confeſs, that in his own account ſhe is not the Church he tells of, truly appointed of God to be this infallible Judge; nor let him thus think to put us off and ſay, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs he evidently prove that ſhe does that by the Pope her mouth: for the Pope will not be content to be the Churches, but Chriſts own mouth
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:32708:23"/> and Vicar, <hi>Peter</hi>'s ſucceſſor, the Rock upon which the Church is built, at leaſt next unto Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Of Proteſtants he ſaith, All that I ever met with ſeemed to grant,<note place="margin">Pag. <hi>18.</hi>
               </note> There muſt be a way or Rule, there muſt be a means appointed, there muſt be a Governing Power to judge and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cide all doubts, and teach us the true way to Heaven with certainty; but who this Judge is, that is the difficulty. Whenas 1. though Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants generally conclude, that the Scripture is the rule according to which every Chriſtian may and ought to judge of doubts with a judgment of diſcretion; and Paſtors joyntly or ſeverally with a judgment of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection: Yet none affirm that any who on Earth is, or can be, either Rule or Judge, much leſs both Rule and Judge Infallible, Univerſal, Praetorial, ſuch as he (under the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his Governing Power) is at preſent ſeeking for.<note place="margin">Pag. <hi>60.</hi>
               </note> Dr. <hi>Fern</hi>'s ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion [indeed ſuch a Judge and Umpire in Chriſtendom if to be had, would be a ready means to compoſe all differences, and to reſtore truth and Peace,] comes next to any that
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:32708:24"/> he can pitch upon, and yet has Dr<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Fern</hi> neither wiſh nor word of any whoſoever being a Rule, nor is he ſo ſawcy as to ſay there <hi>muſt</hi> be a Judge or Umpire appointed. But ſuch a Judge or Umpire would, if to be had, be a ready, neither the beſt nor the only means to compoſe all differences.<note place="margin">Of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibility of the Church of <hi>Rome, p.</hi> 6. §. 19.</note> 2. Sith in thoſe things in which before a General Council hath defined, it is lawful to hold either way, and damnable to do ſo after. The Lord <hi>Falkland</hi> deſire to know how it agreeth with the Charity of the Church to define any thing, and ſo beſtow upon the De<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vil one path more for us to walk in to him.<note place="margin">Againſt <hi>Knot,</hi> part 1. <hi>c.</hi> 2. <hi>pag.</hi> 84.</note> And although, ſayes <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lingworth,</hi> we wiſh heartily that all con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>troverſies were ended, as we do that all ſin were aboliſhed; yet have we little hope of the one, or of the o<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther, till the World be ended: in the mean while think it beſt to content our ſelves with, and perſwade other to, an unity of charity and mutual toleration, ſeeing God hath autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſed no man to force all to the uni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty of opinion. Neither do we think it fit to argue thus: To us it ſeems
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:32708:24"/> convenient there ſhould be one Judge for the whole world; therefore God hath appointed one: but more modeſt and more reaſonable to collect thus, God hath appointed no ſuch judge of controverſies; therefore though to us it ſeems convenient there ſhould be one, yet it is not ſo. And yet, 3. We who can di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh betwixt the ſcriptural way to Heaven, and the Churches Rule of <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ith; betwixt an external infallible Governour, and an internal infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible Teacher; betwixt an unneceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary deciſion of all doubts, and a full ſatisfaction of the heart about the one thing needful: We I ſay, which have learned thus to diſtinguiſh, do humbly and thankfully acknowledge that there is a means appointed to teach us the true way to Heaven with certainty. Jeſus is the true way, the only way to Heaven; and that Spirit which he hath promiſed, and gives in the Goſpel miniſtry, is the means appointed to teach and eſtabliſh us in that way with certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. <hi>If I depart, I will ſend him, unto <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>on, and when he is come, he ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince the world of ſin, becauſe they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:32708:25"/> not in me: They ſhall be all taught of God, all ſhall know me,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>In whom, after that ye believed, ye were ſealed with that holy ſpirit of promiſe, Eph.</hi> 1.15. And now you, inſtead of reviling ſuch Chriſtians as humbly own their having received the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointing, or troubling your ſelf and others with that monſtrous noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of an univerſal infallible govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Church, ſhould examine your ſelf whether you have been ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced, taught and ſealed by that ſpirit through hearing the word of truth, the Goſpel of your ſalvation: <hi>received ye the ſpirit by the hearing of Faith?</hi> Gal. 3.2.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pag. <hi>33.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> It is impoſſible for any one of theſe parties (meaning <hi>Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendents, Presbyterians, Anabaptiſts, Fifth-monarchy</hi> men, <hi>Quakers,</hi>) which I muſt now crave leave to call Sects) with reaſon to cenſure or condemn any of the others, although never ſo different from themſelves, even in points by them eſteemed fundamental, ſince each of them have their uncontroulable Plea for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, that their faith is in every re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect conformable to what they un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:32708:25"/> to be the true ſenſe and meaning of the Scriptures, which they agree to be the ſole and only Rule and Judge. Nay, which of theſe parties can deny the others the Title of Proteſtants, or convince them of Hereſie? Since to be a Proteſtant no more is required (or if it be I would gladly know what it is) than to admit the Scriptures interpreted according to their beſt underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Conſcience, to be the ſole and only rule of Faith, and Judge of Controverſies. Is not he that profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth and followeth this principle, allowed by all to be a perfect good Proteſtant, though never ſo much differing in Faith from others who make the ſame profeſſion.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Quakers,</hi> becauſe your Allies in the grand point of juſtification, and an uncharitable ſentencing of all, ſave their own Sect, ſhall for me ſtand or fall to their own Maſter; but for the reſt that you mention, I ſay that you ſuppoſe what you cannot prove, <hi>ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licet,</hi> that they differ in points that be, or are eſteemed by them to be fundamental. Do they not all own the Creed called the Apoſtles, and
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:32708:26"/> all conclude, that therein be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained all the fundamental points at leaſt? Nay, do they not all own the doctrinal part of the 39 Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, inſomuch that you who would ſeem to revere the Doctrine eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed by Law, dare not ſay they be Hereticks, but are fain to crave leave to call them Sects.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> It's true, they all agree, the Scripture to be the ſole and only Rule, and yet mean the Scripture taken in the ſenſe intended by God, not as privately interpreted by any of them: nor is their faith or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent perſwaſion according to their grounds or pleadings, uncontroula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; ſith what they hold in a ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed conformity with, or under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand to be, the true ſenſe and mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of any Text, is humbly ſubmitted unto what can be made out with greater evidence more nearly to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord with, or be the very ſenſe and meaning intended by the Holy Ghoſt. <hi>Apollos</hi> was ready to yield to <hi>Aquila</hi> and <hi>Priſcilla,</hi> Acts 18.26. and they to you, or any elſe that ſhall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound unto them the <hi>way of God more perfectly.</hi> But,</p>
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:32708:26"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> It matters not much whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther theſe parties can or cannot deny to one another the title of Proteſtant, ſo they ſee ground for, and do al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low to one another the name of Chriſtian: Proteſtant is no more to us, than Papiſt to you, though yet you ſeem not well to know, either who or what is meant by Proteſtant. And therefore ſhall Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> at your deſire inſtruct you: A Proteſtant is a Chriſtian that holdeth to the Holy Scripture, as the ſufficient Rule of Faith and Holy living, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſteth againſt Popery. Or if this like you not, take your own definition with ſome little amendment: A Proteſtant is a Chriſtian, that profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth with S. <hi>Auguſtin,</hi> in thoſe things which are laid down plainly in the Scriptures, all thoſe things are found which appertain to faith and directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of life, and further admitteth of the Scripture where needing inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation: as interpreted according to his beſt underſtanding and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience that he has, or in the uſe of lawful means may have: for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire Rule of what he, as ſuch, ought to hold and practiſe. And yet, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:32708:27"/> all that, and only that required to the Being of a Proteſtant, which you inſert: The parties you tell of, may at that account convince of He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie ſuch amongſt them as ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to be guilty of it; may they not uſe means by <hi>opening, alledging and reaſoning out of the Scripture,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to <hi>Act.</hi> 17.2, 3. better to inform and reclaim ſuch a one? May they not do as the Lay gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man did with you, and you now in writing this Epiſtle do with your old Brethren? or may they not mind him as Chriſt did the <hi>Sadduces? ye err, not knowing the Scriptures,</hi> Matt. 22.19. and make ſuch a like chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge as <hi>Auguſtin</hi> did to <hi>Maximinius.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auguſt. contra Maxim. <hi>l. 3. c. 14.</hi>
               </note> But now neither ought I to produce the <hi>Nicene</hi> Council, nor thou that of <hi>Ariminum,</hi> as going about to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judge, neither am I detained by the Authority of this, nor thou of that ſet thing with thing, cauſe with cauſe reaſon with reaſon, by authorities o<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Scriptures, not proper to either, but common witneſſes to us both, and i<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> after apparent conviction, or ſtop<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ping of the mouth by Scripture Te<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtimony, that man will not relinquiſh
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:32708:27"/> but perſiſt groundleſly to maintain his groſly erroneous Tenet, it is an evident ſign that he does not indeed admit of Scriptures, interpreted ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his beſt underſtanding and conſcience, to be the Rule, but obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately adheres to the perverſe wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful reaſonings of his own fleſhly mind, is not a Proteſtant according to the tenor of your own deſcription; but one that is or ought to be rejected by them. And although I know well enough you have other means for condemning, and killing ſuch you pleaſe to call Hereticks, yet am I to learn, what better means you have whereby to convince them of Hereſie, or diſcern who they be. <hi>A man that is an Heretick, after the firſt and ſecond admonition reject, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that he that is ſuch, is ſubverted and ſinneth, being condemned of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</hi> Tit. 3.10, 11. However you might have done well to have di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed betwixt a Proteſtant, and a perfect good Proteſtant. He that profeſſeth to follow this one principle, ſo diametrically oppoſite to the fundamentals of Popery, may perhaps be admitted by all, or moſt,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:32708:28"/> for a Proteſtant; yet if he differ in points of faith, tradited by the four firſt General Councils, and common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly received by Chriſtians, or to be of a vicious life, he is not, at leaſt ought not to be, owned by any of them for a perfect good Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant.</p>
            <p>To elude theſe plain and evident Texts, <hi>ſcilicet, Deuter.</hi> 17.8. <hi>Matt.</hi> 23.2, 3. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> brought to prove that the Church is the ſole infallible Rule and Judge) you were wont to ſay that they may have other interpretations, and therefore this is not the truth; it is a queſtion whether any Texts of Holy Scriptures, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly whether theſe Texts which ſpeak ſo amply of the Church, are to be underſtood of the Church militant, and viſible in this world, or of the Church triumphant. Ye are willing to agree, that ſo long as the Church of Chriſt teacheth conformable to Scriptures ſhe is infallible. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as inſtead of thus ſaying, doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or agreeing, we enquire,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> To what purpoſe ſhould you urge us to believe the infallibility of the Church, or any thing elſe,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:32708:28"/> upon Scripture grounds, when you tell us aforehand, that faith founded upon Scripture is not truly faith; for though we ſhould grant what you ſuppoſe, <hi>(ſcilicet)</hi> that Chriſt and his Apoſtles did urge the <hi>Jews</hi> with Scriptures, meerly becauſe of their incredulity; yet did they never tell them as you do us: Faith founded upon Scripture will avail you no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. It is not that Divine Faith which God calls for at your hands Or if you yet ſay, that it is warrantable to believe the Church is infallible upon your urging; why not to believe Chriſt to be the Meſſias, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther point of Chriſtian Doctrine, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our Miniſters alledging of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture for it? But,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Be theſe Texts plain and evident, or not? If not, why do you ſay they are? And if they be, theſe very Texts are a Rule, ſuch as you ſeek for, whereby to judge of this Controverſie, and conſequently the Church is not the only Rule where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by Controverſies are to be judged<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But,</p>
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:32708:29"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> The <hi>Quaerendum</hi> here is not whether we can ſhew with any aſſurance, that theſe Texts are capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of other interpretations; but whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you can demonſtrate like as the Apoſtle uſed to do,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Act.</hi> 17.3, 18. theſe your own interpretations to be certainly true; do it, when you do it, by ſome infallible <hi>medium,</hi> and we ſhall be ready to believe what you ſay. But if you bring no proofs; and no other you have brought as yet, ſave your own private reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings. Inſtead of believing the truth of your interpretations, we ſhall make bold to ask you, as you do your ſelf, what difference is there betwixt judging by your own reaſon, and judging by a Law to be interpreted by your own reaſon? This is to make the Scripture not Gods word, but the word of every private man. Though yet,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Had you not made a little bold with your own reaſon, and quite contrary, both to ſenſe and honeſty omitted <hi>verſe</hi> the eight <hi>[be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>between blood and blood, between Plea and Plea]</hi> and put down <hi>&amp;c.</hi> inſtead of the eleventh verſe (<hi>ubi ſatis
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:32708:29"/> apte ſanctus Moyſes Controverſias ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ortas in Populo Dei ex Lege Domini judicandas docet,</hi> Bellar. <hi>de verbo Dei lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 2. according to the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of the Law, which they ſhall teach thee) it would have been evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent from <hi>Deut.</hi> 17. That the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies there ſpoken of, were limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to matters of ſtrife betwixt party and party, like thoſe, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.17. and the Judge in ſentencing, to the Rule of the Law, called <hi>Moſes</hi> Chair, <hi>Matt.</hi> 23.2. And conſequently the firſt Scripture you cite, which ſhould be the meaſure of the reſt, partly makes nothing for, in part makes directly againſt your main concluſion. <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 35.8. hath been already; <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 2.4. <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.20. <hi>John</hi> 16.12. will be hereafter ſpoken to; <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 43.3.17. <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 26.2.1. and <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.9. confirm what we contend for, <hi>(viz)</hi> the whole Church of Gods Elect, conſiſting of lively ſtones to be firm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly built upon that living ſtone, that Rock Jeſus Chriſt. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.4, 5. And that the Royal ſeed, the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God ſhall be all taught and led by the Spirit of God, according to <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.14 <hi>John</hi> 6.45. 1 <hi>John</hi> 2<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:32708:30"/> 27. <hi>John</hi> 14.16. relates only to ſuch as are called out of the world: <hi>love him, and keep his commandements,</hi> as it is evident from <hi>verſes</hi> 15. and 17. concerns neither the Pope nor his Cardinals, unleſs he or they be firſt proved the ſpiritual man intended, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.15. and if <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.11. we may be allowed to leave out the Apoſtles, Prophets, Evangeliſts, and read <hi>he will give,</hi> inſtead of <hi>he gave,</hi> which muſt be done ere that Text can have any ſhew of pertinency, it will reſpect all and ſingular Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors and Teachers that be the gifts of Chriſt: <hi>For the perfecting of the Saints, for the work of the Miniſtry, for the edifying of the body of Chriſt: Till we all come to an unity,</hi> not of opinion, form or points of Faith, as you uſe to word it, but <hi>into the unity of the faith, and knowledge of the Son of God, unto a perfect man, unto the meaſure of the ſtature of the fulneſs of Chriſt: That we henceforth be no more children toſſed to and fro</hi> (from confidence in one device, to a dependency upon ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) <hi>and carried about with every empty wind of Doctrine, by the ſlight of men, and
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:32708:30"/> cunning craftineſs, whereby they lie in wait to deceive. But ſpeaking the truth in love, may grow up to him in all things, which is the head, even Chriſt: from whom</hi> without mention or mediation of any other head, <hi>the whole body fitly joyned together, and compacted by that which every joynt ſupplyeth, according to the effectual working of every part, maketh increaſe of the body, unto the edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying of it ſelf in love:</hi> verſ. 12, 13, 14, 15, 16.</p>
            <p>Nor is the laſt with which you flouriſh, of any more moment: for never to take notice that by Church, cannot there be meant <hi>Roman,</hi> or Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Council: There is a Pillar for holding out Edicts, as well as a Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar for holding up houſes; there is a ground wherein men ſet Trees, ſow Seed, as well as a ground whereon they erect buildings and recumb. The Church may be a Pillar to hold out the truth, and yet not a Pillar for you to rely on for all doctrins that be true. The Church may be that choſen ground, in which the Myſtery of Godlineſs, Chriſt the truth is ſet, and ſown, and yet no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ground given for you to found
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:32708:31"/> your faith upon: Tares may ſpring up together with the good Seed: Truth held out, and yet errour at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend it: However the word in the Greek is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which properly ſignifies a Seat, and you know well how to let <hi>Moſes</hi> Chair alone, and rely on him ſuppoſed to ſit there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in.</p>
            <p>And now Sir, do you not ſtand aſtoniſhed at your own impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in thus impoſing upon the Nonconformiſts; they do not, they need not limit theſe Texts to the Church triumphant, but tell you further,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> That it will be hard for you to prove from Scripture, that the Church of God in this world (the Church you ſpeak of, <hi>Pag.</hi> 62. which Chriſt redeemed with his blood) is a viſible body Politick, different from that inviſible Church which is Chriſts myſtical body: the Texts you cite <hi>Acts</hi> 20.28. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.28. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.11. <hi>Col.</hi> 1.24, 2, 5. <hi>Mat:</hi> 16.18. do import no ſuch thing; for the four firſt diſtinguiſh betwixt the Church and the Overſeers, Officers or Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters thereof; ſeeming thereby to
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:32708:31"/> ſuppoſe that the Overſeers, not as Overſeers in their Politick capacity, but as believers, reſpect had to their ſpiritual Union, be truly members of the Church there mentioned; and for the fifth, if by <hi>Rock</hi> might be underſtood <hi>Peter,</hi> it would as to this buſineſs be of the ſame import.<note place="margin">
                  <p>Auguſtin de verbis domini ſecund. Mat. Serm. <hi>13.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Chamier Tom. <hi>2.</hi> l. <hi>11. chap. 23.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> And if by Rock with the great St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> we underſtand Chriſt (and ſo we ought and may, as is made appear by <hi>Chamier,</hi> the remoteneſs of the ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent notwithſtanding) that Text relates to the Church builded; the Church, which is Gods own work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſhip, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.10. holding out that to be it, againſt which the Gates of Hell, whether ſin or death, or the power or policy of ſpiritual Adverſaries ſhall not prevail.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Your Doctors uſually blame us, for making two Churches, the one viſible and the other inviſible, And now you ſeem offended becauſe we do not. However without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to either, we affirm that the ſame Holy Catholick militant Church, is both viſible and inviſible; inviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, reſpect had to its union, and
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:32708:32"/> viſible reſpect had to its profeſſion of Faith in Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Yours I think do, and therefore ſure ſhould you in this caſe diſtinguiſh <hi>inter Eccleſiam judicantem &amp; docentem</hi> betwixt the Church judging or defining, and the Church teaching, and have pleaded for that, not this to be infallible: as and for ours, though its true, they do af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm that the Church while teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing conformable to Scriptures, teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Doctrine infallibly true, yet do they never ſay that the Church, in any ſenſe is, or ought to be denominated, infallible. No Sir, the Church hath other precious privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, other benefits by theſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, and the Doctrine of Chriſt (as hath and ſhall be made appear) is and may be abundantly otherwiſe confirmed: you need not for fear of debaſing the Church below the Devil, ſuppoſe her thus guilty of robbery, in making her ſelf equal with God: Equal I ſay with God, becauſe infallibility is not an effect or fruit like love, peace, but an eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſential attribute of the Holy Ghoſt,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:32708:32"/> no more communicable to, or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicable either of you or us, than Omnipreſence or Omnipotency: <hi>It's God alone that cannot lie,</hi> Titus 1.2. howbeit, in ſome caſes others through his grace ſhall not.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> The books of Scripture,<note place="margin">Pag. <hi>83.</hi>
               </note> which you are pleaſed to accept as Gods written word, and Divine re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velations, were firſt delivered unto you by Catholicks, and accepted of by your Anceſtors, upon the ſcore and word of Roman Catholicks, Prieſts and Monks, together with the ſame ſenſe and interpretation, which the Roman Catholick Church now teacheth, and which was then confirmed by miracles as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> You confeſs,<note place="margin">Pag. <hi>84.</hi>
               </note> Querie the third, that there is a <hi>Greek</hi> Church, and an <hi>Ethiopian</hi> Church diſtinct from yours; and we can tell you out of <hi>Reinerius cont. Haeret. cap.</hi> 4. of <hi>Leoniſts</hi> or <hi>Lollards,</hi> that were diſperſed into all Countries, have continued ever ſince the Apoſtles, lived juſtly, and believed all the Articles contained in the Creed. Our Anceſtors might receive the books of Scripture as
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:32708:33"/> Gods written word from Catholicks, and yet never be beholding to the Romaniſts for it. But be it ſo, that our Anceſtors did as you ſay, what then? Did not the Primitive Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians receive the books of the Old Teſtament from the Jews, and yet rejected their Traditions, nay, diſputed againſt the Jewiſh Traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons out of thoſe very books. How ever,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Theſe books were not accepted as aforeſaid, upon the ſcore and word of the Roman Catholick Prieſts and Monks; for our Anceſtors had the Prieſts and Monks word for the Apocrypha books, as well as for the Canonical, and yet did they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject thoſe, and accept theſe becauſe they found convincing reaſons ſo to do.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> True it is your Prieſts are ſworn not to interpret Scripture againſt the ſenſe, which the Holy Mother the Church hath held, and doth hold: but that they do ſo, or ever delivered unto our Anceſtors any ſuch an interpretation, much leſs any confirmed by Miracles, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains for you to prove, and is a
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:32708:33"/> fable we know nothing of; though yet,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> If you, your Prieſts and Monks, or any body elſe can bring us to the certain knowledge thereof, or any other traditions ſo confirmed, we ſhall without further ado accept of, hold them as faſt as we can, and in the mean while no little marvel that you knowing ſo well of ſuch a ſenſe, ſhould ſpend time in trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling us with your own private gloſſes. Nor yet is the laſt, the leaſt ſign of a brazen forehead, the Apoſtate bluſhes not to tell to all the world that he has now learned to hate and abhorr Rebellion and Treaſon as much as Hell and Damnation,<note place="margin">Pag. <hi>86.</hi>
               </note> not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding that,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> The general approved Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of <hi>Lateran</hi> under <hi>Innocent</hi> the Third, decrees that if the Temporal Lord being required and admoniſhed of the Church, ſhall neglect to purge his Country of Heretical defilments, the Pope may from thenceforth denounce his Vaſſals abſolved from their fidelity, and may expoſe his Country to be ſeiſed on by Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks, who rooting out the Hereticks
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:32708:34"/> may poſſeſs it without contradiction, and keep it in the purity of Faith. The Popiſh Biſhops and Prieſts declare and ſwear, <hi>extra hanc veram fidem Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicam non eſt ſalus,</hi> out of this true Catholick Faith there is no Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. The ſumm of all the Captain has learned, and would have us to learn, is to believe as the Church be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves: and conſequently is ſo far from having learned to hate and abhor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, as Hell and Damnation; as he believes all ſuch ſhall be dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to Hell, as do not hold it law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful (ſuch procedure firſt had by the Church and Pope) to riſe up in Rebellion againſt their Lord and King.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> The Oath of Allegiance was compoſed and impoſed on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to diſtinguiſh the Loyal and diſloyal Romaniſts, the Popes pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Excommunication not at all therein touched; no point of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine inſerted, and yet is the Popiſh Religion ſo near allied to Rebellion, that it commands her Vaſſals rather to ſuffer death, than bind them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves by Oath to perform Allegiance
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:32708:34"/> to their Lord and King; though yet to ſay truth,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> The Papiſts in this deal more candidly than in any other thing that I know of: for ſhould they take this Oath, as ſometimes ſome of them in policy may do, it were no better than taking Gods name in vain. The Pope if antecedently he have not, may yet at pleaſure abſolve them from it; they may this not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, be free to rebel, ſo ſoon as there is an opportunity, and <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ill there be an opportunity, it is not likely that men ſo wiſe as they, ſhould ever offer to rebel. <hi>Non licet Chriſtianis,</hi> &amp;c. ſays <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> it is not lawful for Chriſtians to tolerate a King that is an Heretick, if he indeavour <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o draw his Subjects into Hereſie: And if you would know how Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Papiſts in <hi>England,</hi> and ſome parts of <hi>Germany</hi> can be excuſed from neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of duty; <hi>Dominicus Bannes</hi> will <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ell you, becauſe that generally they have not power to make ſuch Wars againſt Princes, and great dangers are <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mminent over them, however an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pology might eaſily be framed out of <hi>Bellarmine</hi> in the place fore-quoted,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:32708:35"/> 
               <hi>quod ſi Chriſtiani olim non de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſuerunt Neronem &amp; Diocleſianum, &amp; Julianum Apoſtatam &amp; Valentem Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anum &amp; ſimiles, fuit quia deerant vires temporales Chriſtianis;</hi> If Chriſtians in former times did not depoſe <hi>Nero, Diocleſian, Julian</hi> the Apoſtate, and <hi>Valens</hi> the <hi>Arian</hi> and ſuch like, it was becauſe temporal forces were want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unto Chriſtians: nor may it with any colour of Juſtice be pleaded, that <hi>Bellarmine, Bannes, Mariana, Suarez, &amp;c.</hi> be but private Doctors, unleſs it be firſtly made appear that the Roman Church might, and has legally reverſed the foreſaid <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teran</hi> Decree, and anathematiſed the perſons and opinions of theſe and ſuch like as Heretical; however, Captain <hi>Robert</hi> carries it throughout like a man that is indeed an Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick: for while a Proteſtant, he did act as a rebellious Traytor, and now being turn'd Papiſt will needs profeſs himſelf a Loyal Subject, both in their ſeveral times apparently a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his own principles.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:32708:35"/>
               <head>The ſixth reaſon againſt the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures being a Rule, examined.</head>
               <p>THe ſixth reaſon I meet with, was whatſoever is a ſole and ſufficient rule,<note place="margin">Pag. <hi>42.</hi>
                  </note> muſt be plain and clear in all neceſſary points, at leaſt, which relate unto faith, or the Means by which ſalvation is to be had, which the Scripture is not; and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all things it muſt not contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict it ſelf, which the Scripture ſeems to do. To prove this, I ſhall give ſome few inſtances, which I think can never be infringed.</p>
               <p>The man comes here home to the point, waves his impertinent ſophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical jumbling in of Judge and Guide; and moſt induſtriouſly indeavours to prove from the Scriptures deficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and obſcurity, that it is not the ſole ſufficient Rule, nor is it any mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel that we find him now ſo ſerious and earneſt; for if this argument
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:32708:36"/> fail, all his other ſeven Antiſcriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral reaſons come to nothing with it: for though <hi>Presbyterians, Independents, Anabaptiſts, &amp;c.</hi> ſhould diſagree in matters of Faith, raiſe different ſenſes to ſerve their ſeveral intereſts, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not all of them underſtand, and ſome of them do deſperately wreſt ſeveral places to their own deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the Scripture ſuppoſed plain and clear in all neceſſary points, the fault and folly is their own. The Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture all this notwithſtanding, may and does ſtill remain as it was, a ſole ſufficient Rule; or if ſome Books be loſt, all Copies corrupted, and ſeveral Texts miſtranſlated, yet what's this to the purpoſe, while we can and ſhall evince, that the Books we at preſent have, are ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire, the Copies ſo pure, and the Tranſlations ſo true, that all points neceſſary at leaſt be therein plain and clear; nor will it avail to tell us of the Primitive Chriſtians conſult<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with the Apoſtles, and that it is all one to judge by our own rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and by a Law to be interpreted by our own reaſon: For we might ſuppoſe the Apoſtles with all their
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:32708:36"/> Authority now in being, go and conſult with them, or in their ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence with the Paſtors of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Churches as the great Mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rators of all controverſies, and yet the Scriptures if plain and clear ſtill remain a ſole ſufficient Rule, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to which the controverſies might and ought to be decided: Nor need we in this caſe be trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with interpreting of Scriptures according to our own reaſon, ſith 'tis ſuppoſed, and ſhall be proved, that the Scripture is ſo clear in all neceſſary points, that it needs no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation, though yet you may take notice by the way, that to judge by our own reaſon as the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly rule, is not the ſame with judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by a Law to be interpreted by our own reaſon as one ſpecial means: your Argument would perhaps ſtrike at that; but this is all that in any caſe we practiſe and ſo do; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Chriſt bids us <hi>ſearch the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,</hi> and the Apoſtle adds, <hi>judge ye what I ſay,</hi> comparing ſpiritual things with ſpiritual; however, ſith the faith or means by which ſalvation is to be had, is a believing on Chriſt
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:32708:37"/> the foundation, as hath been ſaid, not a believing of juſt ſo many as you or others are pleaſed to call fundamental points: If the Scriptures be plain and clear, as without perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture they are in their teſtifying of him according to <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.40. they are plain and clear in what neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily relates to Faith, or the means by which Salvation is to be had accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to <hi>John</hi> 20.31. and conſequently what ever becomes of all the other, whether neceſſary or unneceſſary points, may be a ſole ſufficient Rule according to the tendency of this your preſent diſcourſe, the ſeeming contradictions ſhall after your infrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gible inſtances, come now to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſſed.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Pag. <hi>42.</hi>
                  </note>That they are not plain and clear, as aforeſaid, conſider all Chriſtians generally (except ſome few) do agree that the Sacraments of the Goſpel are neceſſary in order to Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation. Now as to theſe, the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures are ſo far from being clear that they do not ſo much as denomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate what a Sacrament is, how many Chriſt ordained, or whether there be any Sacrament or not.</p>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:32708:37"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> All Chriſtians may agree that the Sacraments are neceſſary, and yet they not be ſo; for it's Chriſts ſaying that they are, not at all the Chriſtians agreeing, that can make them neceſſary. Did not all Chriſtians generally agree for ſix hundred years together, that the Euchariſt was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for Infants, and yet now the Church concludeth otherwiſe. But 2. it is here granted that ſome Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians deny the Sacraments of the Goſpel to be neceſſary, and if ſome may be Chriſtians and yet deny the neceſſity of Sacraments, it's an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſufficient that they are not neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary. Nor indeed does the man aſſert that Sacraments be ſimply neceſſary, but qualifies it with, in order to Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, and limits it to Sacraments of the Goſpel: perhaps he may think there be two ways whereby God brings his people to Salvation, one ordinary with, and the other ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary without Sacraments; nor ſhall I ſay more of that, but tell him that if Women and Male Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren under the Law might, much more the <hi>Catechumeni</hi> and Infants under the Goſpel may be ſaved by
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:32708:38"/> grace without Sacraments to confer or convey it. 3. Though it be not the Scripture mode to obſerve Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gick rules in framing definitions, nor always Arithmetical in making up of accounts: Yet is the nature and end of theſe Ordinances we call Sacraments, deſcribed in Scripture ſo far as is meet for us to know: The number numbred, Baptiſm and the Lords-ſupper ſaid to be inſtituted by Chriſt, and no more; and ſure then the man may count two, and need not complain for want of the number numbring.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> It's neceſſary to Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to believe all the Books of Holy Scripture to be the word of God, and to believe nothing written to be the word of God which is Apocryphal; but by the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture it cannot be made out plainly and clearly, which Books are the word of God, and which are Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cryphal.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> Your own Doctors diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh betwixt an affirmative believing and a negative disbelief; and though they make it damnable to disbelieve any one point (when ſufficiently re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:32708:38"/> to the underſtanding as revealed by God) yet do they not make it neceſſary, poſitively and expreſly to believe all, or any of the Books of Holy Scriptures to be ſo revealed; and ſuppoſe they did, it matters not, ſith it's evident that the Scriptures themſelves make believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and not believing all the Books of Holy Scripture to be the word of God, to be that <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>num neceſſarium,</hi> that one thing neceſſary to Salvation. And the Fathers in the Primitive times had differences and doubts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout ſeveral Books of Scripture now commonly received for Canonical, and yet were ſaved by the Grace of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, even as we. 2. Chriſtians convinced by any means whatſoever, that ſuch and ſuch Books in themſelves Apocryphal be the word of God, ought during that conviction believe them to be ſo, and it is ſo far from being neceſſary to Salvation for them, <hi>rebus ſic ſtantibus,</hi> to believ other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, that it were obſtinacy and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretatively a denying of Gods ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racity for them not ſo to believe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mally,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:32708:39"/> as <hi>Chillingworth,</hi> though not materially an Hereſie. 3. True it is that it cannot be made out by Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture as by a Teſtimony, or <hi>Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum inartificiale,</hi> which Books are the Word of God, and which be Apocryphal; yet may this be made out plainly and clearly by Scripture, <hi>Tanquam per Argumentum artificiale, ſcilicet,</hi> The Divine Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters that God himſelf hath im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printed on thoſe Books that be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the Word of God: nor need we trouble your Churches Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, though we confeſs our ſelves much beholding to the Churches miniſtry for the finding of them out.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> It is neceſſary to believe the Scriptures to be the Word of God, but there is no Text or Texts of Scripture to prove that the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures which we have, are Gods Word.</p>
               <p n="1">1. It is neceſſary for you and me to believe the Scriptures to be the Word of God, becauſe we are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, though upon ſeveral grounds, that they be ſo; but that it is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:32708:39"/> for all perſons ſo to believe, will not be granted till you further ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain your [neceſſary,] and add proof for the evincing of it. And yet however, 2. There is a Text of Scripture to prove that the Scriptures which we have are Gods Word; For if there be a Text that expreſly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares that the Scriptures which the Jews and Chriſtians had in the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive times, were the Word of God, there is a Text to prove that the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures which we have, are Gods Word: But there is a Text which expreſly declares that the Scriptures which the Jews and Chriſtians had in the Primitive times were the Word of God; <hi>ergo,</hi> There is a Text to prove that the Scriptures which we have, are Gods Word. The <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor</hi> is evident from univerſal Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion aſſuring us that the Scriptures we now have, be the ſame that the Jews and Chriſtians had then. The <hi>minor</hi> is evinced from that of <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Timothy,</hi> whoſe Mother was a <hi>Jeweſs,</hi> and Father a <hi>Greek; all Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture is divinely inſpired,</hi> 2 Tim. 3.</p>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:32708:40"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> It is neceſſary to know that the Scriptures are not corrupted, for if they be corrupted they ceaſe to be the Word of God, and then they cannot be any rule or ſure guide to us: But of this we have no aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance in Scripture.</p>
               <p n="1">1. It is not neceſſary, as hath been ſaid, to know the Scriptures to be the Word of God; and therefore not neceſſary ſure to know they are not corrupted. Scripture or Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting is no more than one ſpecial means whereby God is pleaſed to make known, and preſerve in the World the knowledge of his Will; if he do it any where by another Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium, that will ſuffice. Nay ſuppoſe, as the man ſeems to do all along, that the Scriptures be corrupted, it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be neceſſary to know that they are not corrupted; unleſs it be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to know that which is not poſſible to be known, and ſo all men be neceſſarily damned. 2. When we ſay, the Scripture is the Rule whereby to judge of Controverſies, it is uſually reſtrained to ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies as do not concern the
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:32708:40"/> Scripture. You will not allow us to argue, the Church is no infallible Judge or Rule, becauſe the Church is forced to ſeek for other and higher proof than her own words to prove her ſelf to be Infallible; and if ſo, why ſhould we argue the Scripture to be no Rule, becauſe we cannot have aſſurance in Scripture that it is not corrupted? it will be ſufficient that we have aſſurance ſome other way. 3. Scripture may be ſaid to be corrupted in Eſſentials or Acciden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals, in whole or in part: It may be corrupted in Accidentals, the Words mis-ſpelled, Sentences miſplaced, Words, or Letters inſerted or omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; and yet the mind and meaning of God what it is, all that notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, be evident from thence. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Book almoſt after its moſt perfect Edition, hath <hi>Errata's,</hi> and yet the Authors meaning may be plain enough: Nay further, Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture may be corrupted in ſome parts, and yet remaining pure in others, <hi>Scriptura per Scripturam,</hi> Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture may be corrected by Scripture, as a Jeſuit of your own hath well obſerved.</p>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:32708:41"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fifthly,</hi> It is neceſſary in order to the knowing of the true mind, mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and will of God, and what he intended by ſuch and ſuch a Text, that we know when a Text is to be underſtood literally, when figura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively, when myſtically; but this cannot be underſtood from Scripture, as daily experience informs us.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Scripture ſuppoſes men to have the uſe of ſenſe and reaſon; and if ſo, they may eaſily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, as ſure as God is truth, the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit ſpake by the Prophets and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles accordingly as he meant; the Prophets and Apoſtles writ according as the Spirit ſpake; and writ for that end, that the true mind, meaning, and will of God might be known and underſtood, which could not be without perpetuated new Revelation, except we might and ought to take that for his mind and meaning which the words in their literal conſtruction hold out unto us. <hi>Eum ſenſum qui ex verbis immedia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te colligitur,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">De verbo Dei, l. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>3</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>certum eſt eſſe ſenſum Spiritus Sancti.</hi> That, ſays <hi>Bellarmin,</hi> which is immediately gathered from
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:32708:41"/> the words, is certain to be the ſenſe of the Holy Ghoſt. And therefore, 2. vainly does he enquire, and fond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſtinguiſh of ſeveral ſenſes of this or that Text, whenas it is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent from the very writing of it in letters, and the confeſſion of our adverſaries, that each Text is to be underſtood literally. Nor is that he calls figurative,<note place="margin">Literalis eſt duplex; alius ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plex, alius figuratu<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Bellar. ibid.</note> any other than a ſpecies of the literal ſenſe: The myſtical, an uncertain remote in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendment of the things, and not the immediate argumentative meaning of the written Words or Text, which we are now enquiring after.<note place="margin">Auguſtin. <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Doctrina Chriſtiana, l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>9.</hi>
                  </note> However, 3. <hi>In iis quae aperte in Scripturis poſita ſunt, inveniuntur illa omnia quae continent fidem moréſque vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vendi:</hi> In thoſe things which are laid down plainly in the Scriptures, all thoſe things are found which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertain to Faith and Direction of Life. Dark figurative Texts, and myſtical meaning of things may in ſome ſenſe be uſeful, yet it is not neceſſary in order to the knowing of the mind of God, ſo far as is requiſite for us to know, that we
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:32708:42"/> ſhould be able to unfold them; <hi>Exponat ſi cui Deus conceſſerit:</hi> As <hi>Cajetan</hi> of the Revelation. And yet further, 4. There is a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betwixt being ignorant of ſuch and ſuch a Text, and wreſting or wilfully perverting it to a wrong ſenſe: This even in Scriptures not materially neceſſary to be known, muſt of neceſſity be avoided. It is Heretical, it is Soul-deſtructive, 2 <hi>Peter</hi> 3.19. that anent Texts holding out points commonly called Fundamental, may conſiſt with ſav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing knowledge; for it is the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the true mind, meaning and will of God as to ſuch a particular that is neceſſary, and not juſt the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it by ſuch and ſuch a Text: you may perhaps know it by one Text, and I by another; or you by oral practical tradition, and I by wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sixthly,</hi> It is neceſſary to know that the very Copies and Tranſlati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Scriptures which we have, and upon which we ground our ſelves, are certainly true: for if they are not, we build upon uncertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:32708:42"/> and conſequently have no ſure foundation for our Faith; yet we cannot be aſſured, nor have ſo much as any information as to this particular from the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> The Man does not deny either the being or poſſibility of knowing, That there be Copies and Tranſlations certainly true; only he aſſerts, That we have not ſo much as any information as to this par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, from the Scriptures, which we might, as hath been ſaid, eaſily grant; and yet upon juſt Grounds maintain that the Scripture is a rule both plain and perfect, howbeit.<note place="margin">In hac ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mani textu<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s perveſtiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione ſalis perſpicuè inter omnes conſtat, nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum eſſe certius ac firmius quam anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quorum pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batorum codicum latinorum fidem, &amp;c. in praefat.</note> we need not do it: for in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſtigation of the true genuine Text, ſays <hi>Sixtus Quintus, There was no Argument more firm and certain to be relyed on, than the Faith of the antient Books: Nor is there a better way,</hi> ſays a great Rationaliſt, <hi>for the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary ſort, whether of Papiſts or Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, than to compare their and our Tranſlations together, and where there is no real difference, there to be confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent they are right: where they differ,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:32708:43"/> there to be prudent in the choice of their Guide.</hi> 2. There is a certainty Mathematical, Moral, and Spiritual. Mathematical, either touching Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies or Tranſlations of Scripture, is not now to be had. Certainty Moral, ſuch as the nature of the thing will bear, and as much as humane Teſtimony and induſtry can afford us, we have: Nor is the building thereupon a founding our Faith upon uncertainties but upon moſt ſtrong probabilities, ſuch as eſpecially in a matter of Fact and Skill it were extream imprudence and obſtinacy, not to reſt ſatisfied withal. Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty Spiritual, whether of Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence or adherence, beyond that which the beſt rational Evidence can give ground for, is to be had, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times <hi>by,</hi> but not <hi>from</hi> us; you muſt by Prayer ſeek unto God for it, every good Gift and every perfect Gift is from above. And if God vouchſafe to give it you as to this particular, touching the whole or part, well; if not, for ought I know, or you are able to evince, you muſt be content to be without it. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:32708:43"/> 3. You do ill to call the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, <hi>quà Scriptura,</hi> as copied and tranſlated, the foundation of Faith; and worſe, to conclude from its un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certainty, as ſuch, that our Faith has no ſure foundation: For Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture under that notion is not the Material, much leſs either the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal or Salvifical object of Faith; nor any more ſave choicely inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental in the producing thereof; and I think we may ſafely affirm, That an Inſtrument in it ſelf fallible, may be mainly ſubſervient to the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Cauſe, in bringing us both to believe Divine Truths, becauſe Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine, and to acquieſce in him who is the Foundation indeed, and Truth it ſelf, Jeſus Chriſt. Your <hi>Engliſh</hi> Prieſts are fallible, yet inſtrumental ſure, by Preaching, Tranſlating, Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, to bring perſons certainly to believe thoſe Propoſals, and to fix upon that Authority, which is ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed in it ſelf to be infallible. <hi>How ſhall they believe in him on whom they have not heard: And how ſhall they hear with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Preacher?</hi> Rom. 10. Not how without an infallible Propoſer.
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:32708:44"/> But, 4. I much admire the Man ſhould hold it neceſſary to know, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſith it is evident that in <hi>Auſtin</hi>'s time, the <hi>Latin</hi> Tranſlations of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture were innumerable, nor could any man have ſaid this or that is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly true: The <hi>Septuagint,</hi> ſaid to be uſed by the Apoſtles, is confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedly faulty: and though ſome of the preſent <hi>Romaniſts</hi> may be arrived at that height of impudence, as perem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptorily to affirm; yet none can ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally make it out, that they know any one Tranſlation that is perfect, or Copy that is uncorrupt. The Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of <hi>Trent</hi> indeed did decree, That the Vulgar Tranſlation ſhould be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived for Authentick; but which ſhe meant by Vulgar, or what by Authentick, no body can yet tell: there was <hi>bellum Papale,</hi> after, about the Editions, <hi>Sixtus</hi> againſt <hi>Clemens,</hi> and <hi>Clemens</hi> againſt <hi>Sixtus.</hi> Nor can their Doctors yet conclude, whether it is better ſay, the Tranſlation is free from all errours, or only ſuch as relate to Faith and Manners.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Seventhly,</hi> It is neceſſary that the many manifeſt controverſies about
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:32708:44"/> the true ſenſe of Scripture ſhould be decided, becauſe where two con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary ſenſes are impoſed and urged, and both affirmed to be the meaning of God, and his Revelation, one only can be true, and he who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſeth that which is true ſhall be dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: yet theſe controverſies cannot be decided by Scripture.</p>
               <p n="1">1. If it be neceſſary that the many manifeſt controverſies about the true ſenſe of Scripture, ſhould be deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; ſure your Supream Infallible Judge is far to blame, that hath not yet decided them, but ſuffers your own Doctors to controvert the ſenſe of almoſt every Text of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture.</p>
               <p n="2">2. We urge, it's true, by Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, but it is you alone that Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſterially impoſe your own meanings as Divine Revelation: and though of two contraries, one ſenſe only can be true, and he that refuſeth that ſenſe which he knows to be true, does deſerve Damnation; yet that God will certainly damn him, or that the not believing in caſe he had not known, were a ſin damnable,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:32708:45"/> is more I think than God ever told you.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Such controverſies as are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to be decided in the uſe of lawful means have been, are, and may be decided by Scripture, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out either compleating it by, or introducing in the ſtead thereof any other Rule; and for the reſt a mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual forbearance of the Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors were far better than your Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torial deciſion of the controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eighthly,</hi> It is neceſſary to know, what is purely and abſolutely ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to Salvation to be believed, and what not; that is, as you ſay, what is fundamental, and what not fundamental; and to be informed of this plainly, leſt we erre and be damned: but in this the Scripture is ſilent.</p>
               <p n="1">1. If it be neceſſary to know what is purely and abſolutely ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to Salvation to be believed, and what not, How comes it to paſs that your Church only declares ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatively what is not to be believed, or what muſt not upon pain of Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:32708:45"/> be disbelieved, and yet never tells affirmatively what is purely and abſolutely neceſſary for us to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve? True, you will have all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve affirmatively, implicitly, what ever your Church believes; but that is nothing to this buſineſs, where knowledge of the [what] in an explicit Faith, is neceſſarily requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. All your Doctors conclude, Somewhat muſt be explicitly believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and you ſay, It is neceſſary to know the Particulars; and yet will not your Church ever be gotten to declare unto us which they be: let her do it when it ſhall ſeem good un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to her; in the interim, I ſhall tell you plainly, That,</p>
               <p n="2">2. So much of the [what] is fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentally neceſſary to be believed, as is needful to bring ſuch or ſuch a perſon to believe in the [who] and reſt on the foundation Jeſus Chriſt; and conſequently more may be neceſſary for one than another, and not neceſſary at all that the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars ſhould be determined. For,</p>
               <p n="3">3. Saving and Damning depends not upon a preciſe knowing and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:32708:46"/> juſt ſo many points, and no more; but upon a hearty believing or not believing in Jeſus Chriſt. <hi>He that believeth in the Son of God, hath eternal life: He that believeth not,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>He that hath the Son hath life, he that hath not the Son hath not life,</hi> 1 John 5.12.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ninthly,</hi> It is neceſſary to believe that God the Father is not begotten; that God the Son is not made but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten by the Father only; that God the Holy Ghoſt is neither made nor begotten, but doth proceed, and that from the Father and the Son; that Chriſt is of one ſubſtance with the Father, and that theſe three are one, and that one three. I refer to conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, whether all theſe points be plainly and clearly to be found in Scripture: If they were, it had been almoſt impoſſible for ſo many divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions to have hapned about them, as have done amongſt perſons on all ſides, admitting the Scripture to be the word of God.</p>
               <p n="1">1. I refer it alſo to conſideration, Whether all theſe points be not plainly and clearly to be found in
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:32708:46"/> Scripture: And wiſh you to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult with almoſt any large <hi>Engliſh</hi> Catechiſm, or common Place book concerning it.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Heart of man is deſperate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wicked, and many are poſſeſſed with a Spirit of blindneſs: It is one queſtion whether all theſe points be plainly and clearly to be found in Scripture? and another, whether all perſons that admit the Scriptures to be the word of God, can or will ſo ſearch as to find them to be there? Both Jews and Chriſtians admit the Books of the Old Teſtament for Divine, and yet differ about the weightieſt, and as we ſay, the clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt point. You ſay the Scriptures are plain and evident for the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches Infallibility: and yet the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, that admit the Scriptures for the Word of God as well as you do, all deny it.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Thoſe ſo manifold diviſions in the Primitive Church, make more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Churches being a Pretori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Judge, than againſt Scripture being a perfect Rule. It had been ſure altogether impoſſible that ſuch
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:32708:47"/> and ſo many points ſhould have been ſo long controverted; but that ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the generality of Chriſtians did not then judge a Pretorial deciſion of controverſies neceſſary, or that there was none then impowered ſo to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cide them. Howbeit,</p>
               <p n="4">4. Is it neceſſary to believe theſe points implicitly or explicitly? if but implicitly; it is not neceſſary in order to the conſtituting of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures an adequate object or rule of believing, than theſe points ſhould be plainly contained in them. For plainneſs reſpects knowledge of the particulars to be believed, which this kind of Faith ſuppoſeth not; and if it be neceſſary to believe theſe points explicitly, knowingly, your own Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors will not deny but that the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures do plainly and perſpicuouſly contain and teach them. <hi>We deny not,</hi> ſaith <hi>Coſterus, that thoſe chief heads of the Faith, which are to all Chriſtians neceſſary to be known to Salvation, are plainly and perſpicuouſly comprehended in the Writings of the Apoſtles.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Enchirid. c. <hi>4.</hi> p. <hi>49.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Cujuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modi ſunt myſterium ſanctiſſimae Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis &amp; incarnationis Filii Dei;</hi> Of
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:32708:47"/> which ſort be the myſtery of the Holy Trinity, and Incarnation of the Son of God. The Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelical and Apoſtolical Books, and the Oracles of the Antient Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, <hi>planè inſtruunt nos,</hi> do plainly inſtruct us what is to be thought concerning things Divine. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hoſtile diſcord laid aſide, let us take the explication of Queſtions, from the words, <hi>Divinely inſpired,</hi> ſays <hi>Conſtantine</hi> to the Council of <hi>Nice:</hi> And now what think ye does <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine</hi> reply? why,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>See</hi> Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min. de ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bo Dei, l. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> he takes oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion hence to ſuſpect <hi>Conſtantine</hi> for a perſon unbaptized, that as yet <hi>non noverit Arcana religionis,</hi> had not been acquainted with the ſecrets of Religion; howbeit better conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, anſwers, 2. That there be Teſtimonies extant in the Holy Scriptures of all the Doctrines which appertain to the nature of God, and that concerning theſe Doctrines, we may be <hi>plenè &amp; planè,</hi> fully and plainly inſtructed out of the Holy Scriptures.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tenthly,</hi> It is neceſſary (the Church of <hi>England</hi> ſaith) that Infants ſhould
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:32708:48"/> be Baptized, and Women ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Holy Sacrament of the Euchariſt, and Chriſtians ſhould ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the Lords-day; and yet none of theſe points are clearly and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly proved from Scriptures</p>
               <p>1. It matters not much what you ſay, elſewhere, this paſſage ſufficiently manifeſts what ſort of Nonconformiſts you write againſt, <hi>ſcil.</hi> not Nonconformiſts to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> but to the Chair of <hi>Rome;</hi> for if otherwiſe, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhould you urge them in this caſe with, The Church of <hi>England</hi> ſaith, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And yet however, 2. You muſt know that if the Church of <hi>England ſay,</hi> It is neceſſary that Infants ſhould be Baptized, it is upon a ſuppoſition that the affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mative may evidently be proved from Scripture; for if you or any elſe ſhall evince that Infants-Baptiſm cannot be proved from the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, the Church of <hi>England,</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle the ſixth, hath expreſly decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red againſt the neceſſity of it. 2. You cannot but have heard of <hi>haec homo, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, Let a Man
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:32708:48"/> examine himſelf,</hi> &amp;c. 1 Cor. 11.28. Women as well as Men are there required, (ſelf examination and not Auricular confeſſion firſt had) to receive the Euchariſt. Nor, 3. Can you be ignorant that there is a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference betwixt the Lords-day be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing neceſſary to be obſerved, and its being neceſſary that Chriſtians ſhould obſerve the Lords-day: That would imply a Doctrinal; This no more than an obediential neceſſity: That if held by any, the Church of <hi>England</hi> will tell you, ought to be proved particularly from Scripture; This needs no more but a general warrant.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eleventhly,</hi> It is a ſin, (as the generality of Chriſtians agree) an hereſie to re-baptize any one, which hath been baptized by an He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retick, where doth the Scripture ſay ſo?</p>
               <p n="1">1. Thoſe that hold it a ſin and hereſie to rebaptize any one,<note place="margin">Videtur quod Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſmus poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit iterari; ſed contra eſt quod dicitur, Eph <hi>4.</hi> una fides, unum bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſma. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quinas <hi>3.</hi> quaeſt. <hi>66.</hi> Art. <hi>9.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>&amp;c.</hi> found their opinion upon Scripture, <hi>One Faith, one Baptiſm,</hi> Eph. 4.5.2. <hi>Cyprian</hi> held, ſuch ought to be re-baptized, dyed in that opinion, and
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:32708:49"/> yet dyed a Saint and Martyr. 3. The Theſis here laid down without reſtriction is apparently falſe, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicting the Nineteenth Canon of the Council of <hi>Nice, Si quis con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fugit ad Eccleſiam Catholicam de Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lianiſt. &amp; Cataphrygiis, ſtatutum eſt rebaptizari.</hi> If any one of the Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lianiſts and Cataphrygians fly unto the Catholick Church, it is De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed, That they ought to be re-baptized.</p>
               <p>And now it being evident that neither your Argument nor in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances make againſt, but for the Scriptures being a ſole ſufficient Rule; let us try what they'll do on that account againſt, or for your <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church. Whatſoever is a ſole ſufficient Rule muſt be plain and clear in all neceſſary points, at leaſt which relate to Faith: But the <hi>Roman</hi> Church is not plain and clear in all neceſſary points that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late to Faith; Therefore the <hi>Roman</hi> Church is not the ſole ſufficent Rule. The <hi>major</hi> is your own, nor ſhall I need to trouble any body elſe for inſtances to prove the <hi>minor.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:32708:49"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt</hi> then it is neceſſary, you ſay, to know how many Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments Chriſt ordained; and yet your Church leaves it doubtful, whether anointing with Oyl was ordained by Chriſt a Sacrament or not; <hi>Inſinuated,</hi> ſhe ſays, it was,<note place="margin">Concil. Trid. Seſſ. <hi>14.</hi> c. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Mark</hi> 6. but does not, dare not, ſay, it was there or any where elſe, inſtituted as ſuch.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> It is neceſſary to ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, you ſay, to believe all the Books of the Holy Scriptures to be the Word of God, and to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve nothing written to be the word of God which is <hi>Apocryphal;</hi> And yet as to this, Your Church is ſo dark and dubious,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>See</hi> Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min. de ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bo Dei, l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>7.</hi>
                  </note> that though <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine</hi> contend that the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> did define the additaments to the Book of <hi>Heſter</hi> to be ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonical; <hi>Sixtus Senenſis</hi> believes otherwiſe, and brings Arguments againſt it. Nay, if it be neceſſary to know which Books be the Word of God and which <hi>Apocryphal,</hi> it is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary ſure to know which Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions be Dominical or Apoſtolical, which not; and yet concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:32708:50"/> this your Church is ſilent.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> It is neceſſary to know that the Scriptures are not corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; it is neceſſary to know when a Text is to be underſtood literal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, when figuratively, when My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtically; it is neceſſary to know that the very Copies and Tranſlations of the Scriptures which we have, and upon which we ground our ſelves are certainly true; it is neceſſary that the many manifeſt controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies about the true ſenſe of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture ſhould be decided; it is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to know what is Fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal, what not: and yet as to none of theſe your Church is plain and clear.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> It is neceſſary to believe that God the Father is not begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten; that God the Son is not made but begotten by his Father only; that God the Holy Ghoſt is neither made nor begotten, but proceedeth from the Father and the Son; that Chriſt is of one ſubſtance with the Father, and that theſe Three are One, and that One Three: and yet ſuppoſe theſe points not plainly and clearly
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:32708:50"/> to be found in Scriptures, how poſſibly could the Church for the firſt three hundred years be ſaid to be plain and clear concerning them? for during that time there was no General Council whereby ſhe might explain her ſelf, and if ſhe did ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain her ſelf in General Councils after, that implyed her former dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and deficiency, with reſpect to thoſe very points.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fifthly,</hi> It is a ſin and hereſie, you ſay, to re-baptize any one who hath been Baptized by an Heretick; and yet as hath been ſaid, your Church, that I mean you take the boldneſs to call your Church, is ſo far from being plain and clear in this, that ſhe hath defined the contrary: Nay, plainneſs and clearneſs owned as it is, and ought to be, for an eſſential property of the Rule of Faith,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 54, 56.</note> the whole of what you have ſaid in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half of the Church (if granted true) will amount to as much as nothing. For ſuppoſe Chriſt judge the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions not by his Word and Spirit in the mouths of his Miniſters, but, as you phraſe it, by his Churches Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunal
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:32708:51"/> in paſſing of Acts and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing Anathema's; ſuppoſe the Church to be what you would have it, and not only led, if ſhe will, but ſo drawn that ſhe follow the Spirit into all truth, <hi>&amp; ſic de caeteris,</hi> yet what were all this to the purpoſe? For it would not neceſſarily follow thence that ſhe is plain and clear in all neceſſary points: the Apoſtles ſure, if any, might ſo judge and were ſo drawn,<note place="margin">Pag. <hi>37.</hi>
                  </note> and yet you ſay that they in their Epiſtles are defective, dark, very ſubject, and that in fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentals, deſperately to be miſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood. Nor do you trouble us with telling that the Church is always in being,<note place="margin">Pag. <hi>61.</hi>
                  </note> and capable upon demand to explain and declare its own ſenſe; For 1. If we cannot certainly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the Apoſtles, when explaining and declaring their ſenſe and mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, how ſhall we be able certainly to underſtand your Church, when explaining and declaring hers, ſith the Church hath no other way to explain her meaning, ſave by words moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligible, which way the Apoſtles
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:32708:51"/> had, and did make uſe of as is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent from 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.2. The queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is, whether the Church be actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally plain and clear in all neceſſary points; not whether the Church be capable upon demand to explain and declare its own ſenſe: being plain and clear, and capable upon demand to explain and declare, be different things; this belongs to an Interpreter, of no concern here, it's that that is pertinent and the property of a Rule. And yet 3. The Church diffuſive is not capable either of explaining or of being demanded to explain its own ſenſe: Council or Church re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentative, there has been none at your own account for a whole Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tury of years, nor likely to be any more, and it cannot be imagined that by Church you ſhould mean the Pope, becauſe, other reaſons at preſent omitted, you referr to a Church always in being: However, 4. <hi>Fruſtra eſt potentia quae non redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citur in Actum:</hi> What are we near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er having, or the Church nearer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:32708:52"/> a Rule of Faith, for her being capable of doing that, which by no means ſhe'l be gotten to do? Often has ſhe been demanded, I now de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, and deſire you to demand her, to explain her ſelf touching the points forementioned, as alſo touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thoſe after inſtanced in the cloſe of my anſwer to the third Querie; and if ſhe do explain her ſenſe as to thoſe points, we ſhall conclude that hitherto ſhe hath not been a ſole ſufficient Rule, for want of that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planation; if ſhe do not, at the beſt ſhe'l be but remotely capable of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hereafter, and at preſent be no Rule of Faith; nor yet indeed is ſhe capable at this account of being here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, or rather, would you ſpeak properly, making ſuch a Rule, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe diſenabled by the firſt general Council at <hi>Epheſus</hi> from ever mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>tanquam de fide</hi> any ſuch an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planation.<note place="margin">Can. 7.</note>
               </p>
               <p>That there are in the Scriptures ſeveral places which to common reaſon ſeem contradictions, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently ſome parts of Scripture
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:32708:52"/> ſeem untrue, is eaſily proved: And I ſhall here give you ſome few plain inſtances for example, to which ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more might be added.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> It's well you diſtinguiſh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt private and common Reaſon; for though you exempt each mans pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Spirit or Reaſon, from meddling about interpreting of Scriptures, you'l ſure admit common Reaſon to be of ſpecial uſe, unleſs you'l ſay that Reaſon ought to be abuſed for finding out of contradictions in Scriptures, but muſt by no means be employed ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in unfolding or reconciling the difficult places that occur there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> Either Reaſon can judge of things and propoſitions, when con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictory, or not: if not, wherefore do you tell ſtories of ſeveral places ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to common Reaſon to contradict one another, ſo ſeeming that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Scripture muſt be rejected from being a Rule; and if Reaſon can thus judge, wherefore ſhould not your Church be rejected from being a Rule as well as Scriptures, ſith her
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:32708:53"/> Doctrines ſeem to Reaſon, and often to common Senſe too, to be more contradictory than any of theſe Texts. A Council is above the Pope: A Council is not above the Pope: <hi>hoc</hi> this <hi>ſcilicet</hi> bread or nothing, is the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, is really Chriſts body at <hi>London,</hi> at <hi>Rome,</hi> on Earth, in Heaven, the very ſame moment. Every man is a lyar; The Pope as Pope is a man, (unleſs he be either <hi>Accidens</hi> or <hi>animal irrationale</hi>) and yet the Pope as Pope is no lyar, in no poſſibility to be miſtake. Nay further, theſe very places you ſay ſeem contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory, your Church teaches to be certainly true in her Authoritative approval of the Canon of Scripture: ſo that if upon this account you'l reject Scripture, upon the ſame account you may, muſt reject the Church from being a Rule: and yet rather the Church than the Scripture, for the Scripture barely preſents us with the places; your Church paſſeth ſentence, ſays they are all true: un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs you'l tell us your Churches ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing can make contradictions true at
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:32708:53"/> once, and warrant you to believe it; howbeit Gods ſaying cannot do ſo.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Had you had many more plain inſtances, it is not like you would have troubled the Reader with theſe: your task is to prove, that the Scripture is not plain and clear in all neceſſary points: and is it not then for want of ſome more pertinent, that you preſent us with doubts and difficulties about Chronologies and Genealogies, concerning which the Apoſtle forbids us to diſpute: you had better have ſaid with the great Maſter of Reaſon, <hi>Grotius, afflatu Dei locutos quae locuti ſunt, ſcripſiſſe quae ſcribere juſſi ſunt Prophetas; de ſcriptis Hiſtoricis &amp; Moralibus Hebraeorum ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiis aliud puto.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In 2 <hi>Kings chap.</hi> 8. verſe 26. you read thus,<note place="margin">Pag. <hi>45.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Twenty two years old was Ahaziah when he began to reign, and he reigned one year in Jeruſalem; and his Mothers name was Athaliah, the Daughter of Omri.</hi> But 2 <hi>Chron. chap.</hi> 22. verſe 2. you will read thus, <hi>Forty and two years old was Ahaziah
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:32708:54"/> when he began to reign, and he reign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed one year in Jeruſalem; his Mothers name was Athaliah the daughter of Omri.</hi> Now againſt the infallibility of Scripture, Reaſon conceiveth her ſelf to have this infallible demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration, <hi>viz.</hi> No one who ſpeaketh two things, the one contrary to the other, can be ſaid to be infallible in ſpeaking: but to affirm of the ſame perſon that he began to reign when he was two and twenty years old, and that he was two and forty years old when he began to reign, is to ſpeak two things, the one con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the other; therefore ſaith Reaſon, the Scripture is not infallible in ſpeaking.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> I am glad to find you in hand with infallible demonſtrations: for if demonſtrations Theological be to be had, and may be owned as infallible, I hope there will be no great need amongſt ſober per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, of your judicial Deciſions, unleſs you can get licence to demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate againſt, and we neither for, by, nor from the Scriptures.</p>
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:32708:54"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> Your Major is denyed; for heat and cold are two things contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one to another, and yet I hope God himſelf may be infallible, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding he hath ſaid, <hi>Summer and Winter, heat and cold, Gen.</hi> 8.22. You would ſay if you could ſpeak, No one that delivereth two propoſitions, the one contrary to the other, can be ſaid to be infallible; though yet this will not do neither, for you your ſelf might ſpeak and write too theſe two propoſitions, <hi>Ahaziah began to reign when he was forty and two years old: And Ahaziah began to reign when he was twenty and two years old,</hi> and yet this notwithſtanding, did nothing elſe hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, be infallible. But that it may be ſenſe and pertinent, your Major muſt be ſupplied from your Minor: No one that affirms two things of the ſame perſon that are contrary the one to the other, can be ſaid to be infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in ſpeaking: But to affirm of <hi>Aha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ziah,</hi> that <hi>he was twenty and two years old when he began to reign;</hi> and that <hi>he was forty and two years old when he began to reign,</hi> is to ſpeak two things
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:32708:55"/> contrary the one to the other; yes, and more too, or elſe nothing to the purpoſe, <hi>ſcilicet,</hi> to affirm of the ſame perſon two things contradicto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one to the other,<note place="margin">See <hi>Light-foots</hi> Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony in <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>oc.</hi>
                  </note> which yet this Scripture doth not: for the Book of <hi>Chronicles</hi> in this place meaneth not that <hi>Ahaziah</hi> was ſo old <hi>when he began to Reign;</hi> but theſe <hi>two and forty years,</hi> have relation to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing, namely to the Kingdom of the Houſe of <hi>Omri,</hi> and not to the Age of <hi>Ahaziah;</hi> for count from the beginning of the reign of <hi>Omri,</hi> and you find <hi>Ahaziah</hi> to enter his Reign in the two and fortieth year from thence.</p>
               <p>The Original words therefore <hi>Ben arbagumi <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſhethaiim Shunah</hi> are not to be tranſlated as they be, <hi>Ahaziah</hi> was two and forty years old, but <hi>Ahaziah</hi> was the Son of the two and forty years, as <hi>Sedar Olam</hi> hath acute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obſerved long ago: nor ſhould you tell us now of our different tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, unleſs it could be made ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear that the Church in all ages had, and of neceſſity ought to have one authentick Tranſlation. Or,</p>
               <pb n="99" facs="tcp:32708:55"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> that our Tranſlations do not clearly and with one conſent deliver to us all points neceſſary to be believed, differing only in ſome punctilio's of an inferiour concern. Or,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> That it may not be as lawful for us to propoſe what ſeems agreeable to Reaſon for the remov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as 'tis for you to urge what ſeems contradictory to Reaſon, for the rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of objections againſt a book of Scripture ſo univerſally received for Canonical: And your Minor thus mended, is denyed; for contradicto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries muſt be <hi>ad idem,</hi> in the ſame reſpect, as well as <hi>de eodem,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>See</hi> Peter Martyr<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                     <hi>in</hi> loc.</note> concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſame perſon. <hi>Ahaziah</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to reign with his ſickly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm Father when he was twenty and two years old, and the ſame <hi>Ahaziah</hi> was forty and two years old when he began to reign him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf alone: or if this will not ſatisfie, you may conſult with your own <hi>Cornelius de lapide</hi> upon the place, he'l tell you of the <hi>Syriack</hi> and <hi>Arabick</hi> Tranſlations, both thoſe of <hi>Antioch</hi> or
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:32708:56"/> Mount <hi>Sinai,</hi> the <hi>Alexandrian</hi> or <hi>Cop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick,</hi> that for <hi>forty two,</hi> have <hi>twenty two;</hi> and he that is offended at the other, may uſe this reading. Nor is it, ſaith he, the interpreters, but the Scripture it ſelf that corrects it ſelf, corrupted by the Tranſcribers: The book of <hi>Kings</hi> corrects the book of <hi>Chronicles:</hi> nor need we go further than Scripture for ſalving of the other difficulties; for 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 3.16. will teach you to inſert <hi>Joechim</hi> or <hi>Jachim</hi> betwixt <hi>Joſias</hi> and <hi>Jeconiah, Mat.</hi> 1.11. and ſo compleat your number of forty two; and <hi>Gen.</hi> 10.22. will tell you to put out <hi>Cannai</hi> from betwixt <hi>Sem</hi> and <hi>Arphaxad,</hi> put in upon ſpecial Reaſon, as is conceived by the Seventy,<note place="margin">See <hi>Light-foots</hi> Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony in <hi>loco.</hi>
                  </note> and retained as is likely by S. <hi>Luke chap.</hi> 3.36. the better to win upon the Gentiles.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="101" facs="tcp:32708:56"/>
               <head>The Argument from Heaven, for the Roman Churches being Judge and Guide, ſolved.</head>
               <p>ANd now that I may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude my whole proof with an Argument from Heaven,<note place="margin">Pag. <hi>74.</hi>
                  </note> and by a Teſtimony of the higheſt nature make it evident to you, that this Roman Catholick Church muſt be this Church, which God hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to be this Guide and Judge, I ſhall inſiſt upon the gift of Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles; this was that Teſtimony which our bleſſed Redeemer did himſelf produce, as his Letters of Credence, and as both neceſſary and ſufficient to prove his miſſion, <hi>If I had not</hi> (ſaith our Lord, <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.24.) <hi>done among them the works that no other man did, they had not had ſin,</hi> namely, <hi>in not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving me to be the Meſſiah.</hi> God
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:32708:57"/> therefore hath decreed it as a Law, that whoſoever refuſeth to believe and ſubmit unto that authority, unto which he ſets his hand and Seal, by beſtowing on it the gift of Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, that Perſon committeth ſin: the reaſon is given in the ſame Text, <hi>viz.</hi> becauſe he thereby ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that he hateth God, namely by not believing him. Now I urge, But the Roman Catholick Church hath done Works and Miracles a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us, ſuch as no other Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Church upon Earth hath done; Therefore if we give credit to any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Church or Churches, and disbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve or refuſe to believe her, we ſhall have ſin, and ſhew our ſelves to be haters of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> You pretend here to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude your proof with an argument from Heaven, and yet have you not hiththerto produced ſo much as one Teſtimony of the loweſt na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; ſomewhat you have ſaid in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, which is already touched, to prove what we grant, <hi>ſcilicet,</hi> that no other Church can be; but have
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:32708:57"/> not ſaid a word to make good what you your ſelf affirm, <hi>viz.</hi> that the Roman Church is, this infallible Rule, Judge and Guide. And let me tell you by the way, either you can prove this your Church infallible, or you cannot: If you cannot, wherefore ſhould we believe it? If you can, either by Revelation, or by Reaſon: Divine revelation, it's apparent, you nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do, can, nor attempt to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce: and as for Reaſon, you have already proved it to be fallible; ſo that at beſt, how much ſoever you may ſeem to be taken with your own fallacies, your Church can be proved but fallibly to be infallible. But,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> There is a difference betwixt the gift, and the power of working Miracles. You do, it's true, inſiſt upon the gift, but ſhould make it out that your Church has power of working Miracles, if you'l evince her, Chriſt-like, to be infallible: this was neceſſary; that had not been ſufficient to have proved his miſſion: It is therefore ſomewhat looſe arguing, for you to conclude, the
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:32708:58"/> 
                  <hi>Jews</hi> committed ſin, were haters of God, for not believing Jeſus to be the Meſſiah, who did amongſt them the work which no other man did, <hi>viz.</hi> wrought Miracles by his own power; and therefore Chriſtians commit ſin, ſhew themſelves haters of God in not believing the Roman Church to be infallible, becauſe ſhe has the gift, can do works (howbeit, none among us) like other men, <hi>viz.</hi> work Miracles in the name and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of another. And hence,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> We deny Gods having decreed any ſuch a Law as you tell of;<note place="margin">1 Sam. 10. Numb. 11.</note> for though an Authority, to which God ſets his hand and ſeal, by beſtowing on it the gift of Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, may be rendred thereby (like that of <hi>Saul</hi> and the Seventy, by the ſpirit of Prophecy) more than ordinary venerable; and whoſoever refuſeth to believe and ſubmit to an Authority, knowing it to work Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles by its own power, that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon committeth ſin, and ſheweth himſelf an hater of of God: yet may an Authority divinely ſigned
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:32708:58"/> and ſealed by having that gift, be disbelieved (however, ſubmiſſion ſtill due whether it have the gift or not) without contracting any ſuch a guilt: not disbelieved, do I mean, in a particular Doctrine, that it ſhall actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally and viſibly confirm by Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles; but disbelieved, when teaching it ſelf and all other Authorities that have that gift, to be disbelievable upon that account, or <hi>de debito</hi> believed in all that they ſhould dictate forth unto us: That being indeed a Doctrine never confirmed by Miracles, nor delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by him that had the power of working of them. Though yet,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> It cannot be made out that Chriſt did ſet his hand and ſeal either to this or that Authority, by beſtowing on it any ſuch a gift; for particular believers had that gift be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed upon them, as well as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles; <hi>theſe ſigns ſhall follow them that believe,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Mark.</hi> 16.17. Nor did the Apoſtles work Miracles by virtue of their Authority, but by Faith; <hi>If ye have Faith as a grain of Muſtard-ſeed,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Matt.</hi> 17.20. <hi>And though
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:32708:59"/> I have all Faith,</hi> &amp;c. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.2. And <hi>when Peter ſaw it, he anſwered unto the People, Ye men of Iſrael, why marvel ye at this? or why look ye ſo earneſtly on us, as though we by our own Power and Holineſs, had made this man to walk? His name through Faith in his name hath made this man ſtrong,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>yea the faith which is by him, hath given him this perfect ſoundneſs in the preſence of you all,</hi> Act. 3.12, 16. And hence ſure it is, that in your Minor you leave out Authority, mention neither Seal nor Gift, but barely urge and aſſume — Now the Roman Catholick Church hath done, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> not now God hath ſet his hand and ſeal to the Authority of the Roman Catholick Church, by beſtowing upon it the gift of Miracles: Nor is it any marvel that you do ſo, for if that gift were beſtowed upon that Authority, the Pope and Council that are inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted with it, ſhould work Miracles, which yet they do not, nor do you inſiſt on any ſuch a thing; and yet if that gift be not beſtowed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:32708:59"/> that Authority, it cannot beſtow <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t upon inferiour Officers: it wants Gods Hand and Seal, and may ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the tenor of your own Argument be disbelieved, be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obeyed, without either committing ſin, or ſhewing hatred againſt God. However, 5. If a Church may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly be ſaid to work Miracles, when yet indeed it is not the Church, but ſome particular believer that works them, and that not in the name of the Church, but in the name of Chriſt; Other Chriſtian Churches have done as great Works or Miracles in former Ages as the <hi>Roman</hi> Church ever did; witneſs the Church of <hi>Corinth, that came behind in no gift,</hi> 1 Cor. 1.7. and yet were not they reputed thereupon either Judges of controverſies, or infallible; nor does the preſent <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Church do any greater Works or Miracles than other Chriſtian Churches now on earth. What does ſhe, what can ſhe do here amongſt us, more than our Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Church doth (amongſt you,)
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:32708:60"/> ſave make louder lying boaſts of what ſhe has done elſewhere? And therefore ſhall not we refuſe to believe them, or reſolve to give credit unto her upon any ſuch ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, and conclude our ſo doing to be warrantable, and well enough conſiſtent with the love we owe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lord; wiſhing you yet with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al to remember, That the Queſtion is not ſolely or chiefly whether this or that Church ought to be believed or disbelieved in their Doctrinal teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; but whether the <hi>Roman</hi> Church be the infallible Rule, Judge, and Guide of Faith? Doctrinal cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty will not infer Judicial Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, nor <hi>è contra:</hi> Nay ſuppoſe your Church were Doctrinally in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible, and had univerſal Juriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, yet would it not neceſſarily fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low that ſhe is the Rule of Faith. The Prophets of old, you will ſay, were infallible, and the High Prieſts had judicial power, and yet <hi>to the Law and to the Teſtimony,</hi> Iſaiah 8.20. It was therefore prudently done of you to alter the Queſtion,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:32708:60"/> Firſt leave out Rule, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake to prove no more by your Argument from Heaven, but that the <hi>Roman</hi> Church was Judge and Guide; and then find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing after a while, that that would not do neither, you leave out Judge or Authority, and tell us of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving and disbelieving, as if it would follow, The <hi>Roman</hi> Church ought to be believed in all that ſhe ſays, and therefore has ſhe plainly ſaid all that we ought to believe, is a Rule of Faith compleat and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident; howbeit indeed, had ſhe authoritatively and infallibly ſo ſaid, not ſhe, but her ſayings in propriety of Speech were to be owned for the Rule.</p>
               <p>Now that the <hi>Roman</hi> Church hath done theſe works or Miracles,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 76.</note> is a thing ſo evident both by the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of the Holy Fathers, and authorities of approved Hiſtorians, that thoſe who deny it muſt ſhew themſelves either not to be Men, or Men who purpoſely ſhut their Eyes againſt the truth; yea, Heathens
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:32708:61"/> and Atheiſts will be as juſtifiable in their denial of the Miracles re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated in the Old and New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as thoſe will be who deny theſe. The <hi>Magdeburgenſes,</hi> who were all profeſſed and known <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therans,</hi> do almoſt in every one of their Centuries recount multitudes of Miracles wrought by perſons whom they affirm to have been infected with what they call Popery. Namely, S. <hi>Bernard,</hi> S. <hi>Malachy,</hi> S. <hi>Dominick,</hi> S. <hi>Francis,</hi> and the like; as you may particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly ſee in <hi>Brerely,</hi> if you ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine the ſeveral places to which his Index at the word Miracles will refer you: By which it will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, That moſt of thoſe Miracles were done not in confirmation of thoſe Points and Articles of Faith which you hold with us; but even of thoſe Points and Doctrines which you call Popiſh Superſtitions and Idolatries, as the Sacrifice of the Holy Maſs, the reſpect and venera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which is given to Saints, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques, Images, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Certainly there
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:32708:61"/> are few amongſt you, but have heard and read, how and what Chriſtian Faith was firſt brought into <hi>England</hi> amongſt our Progeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors the <hi>Saxons,</hi> and by whom brought in: It was by S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> a Monk of S. <hi>Benets</hi> Order, and his fellow Monks, ſent hither by S. <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory</hi> the then Pope of <hi>Rome;</hi> and it was the ſame Faith that Catholicks now teach, which was then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by wonderful Miracles from Heaven, as is teſtified by our own Writers, Venerable <hi>Bede</hi> and others; yea and by our Proteſtant Chrono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logies, <hi>Holingſhead</hi>'s Chronicle, the laſt Edition, Vol. 1. Book 5. Cap. 21. Page 100, 102. <hi>Fox</hi>'s Acts and Monuments, Printed <hi>Anno</hi> 1576. Pag. 117. <hi>Stow</hi>'s Annals, Printed 1592. Pag. 66. <hi>Goodwin</hi> in his Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talogue of the Biſhops of <hi>England,</hi> Pag. 4. Alſo <hi>Fox</hi> in his aforeſaid Book, at the Word Miracles in the Index. To this I ſhall add the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorities of our own late Proteſtant Writers, for proof of undoubted Miracles wrought in this latter Age.
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:32708:62"/> In the Book entituled, <hi>A report of the Kingdom of</hi> Congo, <hi>a Region of</hi> Africa, Printed <hi>Anno</hi> 1597. Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed by Mr. <hi>Abraham Hartwel,</hi> Servant to the Lord Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> mention is made, <hi>Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Cap.</hi> 1. of the diſcovery of that Kingdom, 1587. by <hi>Odoardo Lopez,</hi> and of the converſion thereof to the Chriſtian Faith, <hi>Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>Cap.</hi> 2. and of the great and undoubted Miracles ſhewed by God in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of a whole Army, <hi>Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>Cap.</hi> 3. Inſomuch that the ſaid <hi>Hartwell,</hi> in his Epiſtle there to the Reader, confeſſeth, That this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion of <hi>Congo</hi> was accompliſhed by Maſſing Prieſts, after the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh</hi> manner; and ſaith he, this action which tendeth to the glory of God, ſhall it be concealed and not committed to memory, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it was performed by Popiſh Prieſts and Popiſh means? God forbid. In like manner Mr. <hi>John Pory</hi> of <hi>Gonvile</hi> and <hi>Cajus</hi> Colledge in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> in his Geographical Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of <hi>Africa,</hi> publiſhed <hi>Anno</hi>
                  <pb n="113" facs="tcp:32708:62"/> 1600. Pag. 410, 413. commendeth Mr. <hi>Hartwel</hi> for publiſhing the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid Miracles, and acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the ſame.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The common people may, muſt be deluded by lying Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders: but ſith you are ſo ſober as not to inſiſt upon our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Prieſts, either throwing in, or throwing out of Devils; you did wiſely, when giving in your Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue of Miracles done by the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh</hi> Church, to leave out [amongſt us] and yet ſuppoſe the <hi>Roman</hi> Church hath done theſe Miracles, and done them [amongſt us] it is little to the point; for if ſhe did them in her own name and power, ſhe is no more a Church but a God, the Meſſias; and if ſhe did them in the name and power of Chriſt, it will evince Chriſt, in whoſe name and power the Miracles were wrought, to be the Son of God, and conſequently infallible; but leave your Church ſubject to mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtakes as formerly ſhe was. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, 2. It is one thing to ſay, it is
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:32708:63"/> evident both by Teſtimonies of Holy Fathers and approved Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians; and another thing to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce thoſe Teſtimonies: and yet if you had, thoſe Teſtimonies could be no more than Humane, capable of miſtake, in a poſſibility of being erroneous, and conſequently the thing as to us, be no more at your own account, than probably true; our belief, or opinion rather, no better founded than the perſwaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Jews, Turks, or Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans; all upon a fallible certainty. Nor yet, 3. Can it be ſaid either with truth or modeſty, that the Heathens and Atheiſts will be as juſtifiable in their denials of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles revealed in the Old and New Teſtament, as thoſe Men will be that deny theſe. For though the relation of the Miracles in the Old and New Teſtament be brouhgt down to us by humane means, yet ſuch as be in no wiſe (morally) queſtionable; and beſides, all is ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timately reſolved into Teſtimony Divine: Whereas theſe reports of
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:32708:63"/> yours, firſt and laſt, have no firmer a Baſis than the Teſtimony of Men blinded, byaſſed by intereſt, and that could not certainly know a true Miracle from a lying Wonder, had they ſtood by at the working there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. 4. It may be true that the <hi>Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deburgenſes,</hi> with ſome others, writing the Churches general Hiſtory, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count as from your own Authors, ſeveral Miracles to have been done by perſons infected with Popery: But it is as true that they themſelves account of them all as no better than either illuſions of Daemons, or falſe narrations. And well may we grant with <hi>Abraham Hartwell, John Pory,</hi> and ſome more of ours, True Miracles to have been wrought by Popiſh perſons; and not conclude with you, Popiſh, but Chriſtian Doctrine to have been confirmed by them: For if they did Miracles, it is apparent they did them as Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, and not as Papiſts, in the name of Chriſt, and not in the name of the Pope; nor need you ſtumble at ſuch a diſtinction.<note place="margin">Bellar. de Notis Eccleſ. l. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>14.</hi>
                  </note> For <hi>Bellarmin</hi>
                  <pb n="116" facs="tcp:32708:64"/> unto the Miracle of <hi>Novatianus</hi> the Heretick, anſwereth, the Miracle to have been wrought not for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of the Faith of <hi>Novatia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> but of Catholick Baptiſm. And yet ſuppoſe Miracles wrought to confirm the truth of certain Popiſh Doctrines, what is that to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibility of the Popiſh Church? that learned Cardinal ſaw the <hi>non ſequitur</hi> well enough; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore labours by Miracles to prove the verity, not the infallibility of that Church, and to prove it by them credibly, not certainly. For ſaith he, before the approbation of the Church, it is not evident or cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain with the certainty of Faith con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning any Miracle that it is a true Miracle. However, 5. The moſt antient Author you or your Index pretend to quote, is <hi>Beda,</hi> who flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed <hi>Anno</hi> 720. the moſt antient Miracle-Monger, the Monk <hi>Auſtin,</hi> who came into <hi>England</hi> about the Year 600. an evident ſign that your Popiſh Doctrines, if brought forth, yet were not confirmed from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:32708:64"/> for the firſt ſix hundred years after Chriſt: Nor were thoſe you inſtance in, ratified on Earth by any General Council for a long time af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that. The firſt pretended for Image-Worſhip is the ſecond of <hi>Nice, Anno</hi> 705. condemned by that of <hi>Frankford, Anno</hi> 794. And the firſt for Tranſubſtantiation was that of <hi>Lateran,</hi> 1215. For the moſt notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous of the reſt you muſt come down as low as the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun ſince <hi>Luther</hi>'s death. And for a Miracle neither <hi>England, France, Italy</hi> nor <hi>Spain</hi> can furniſh you with one; but you are forced to run as far as <hi>Congo,</hi> a Kingdom in the Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Africa,</hi> and there reſolve your Faith into a Book, ſaid by <hi>John Brerely, Anno</hi> 1664. to have been publiſhed <hi>Anno</hi> 1597. by <hi>Abraham Hartwell</hi> Servant to the Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury</hi> (without any leave from his Maſter) which Book yet, for ought appears, neither mentions Miracles done to confirm the truth of any Popiſh Doctrine, nor the Infallibility of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church.</p>
               <pb n="118" facs="tcp:32708:65"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Pag. <hi>78.</hi>
                  </note> If any of you ſhould chance to ſay, That this Teſtimony of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles is nothing to you, becauſe you have never ſeen a Miracle: I anſwer, Either you grant what theſe Authors report, to be true, or you deny their Teſtimony, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſing to believe what you have not ſeen. If you grant the truth of theſe things, and yet remain out of the Communion of the Holy Catholick Church, upon which God hath conferred this Gift, you have ſin, and hate God, according to the argument framed by our Lord him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, which I have before cited. <hi>If you refuſe to believe what you have not ſeen,</hi> Firſt, You deſtroy Faith, <hi>Which is an evidence of things not ſeen.</hi> Secondly, You take away all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane converſation; no man muſt believe another. Thirdly, you make it unjuſt for Civil Magiſtrates to puniſh Tranſgreſſors or Felons: for where there is no Law, there can be no breach of a Law; and if there be no Law to him who did not actually ſee the very Statute
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:32708:65"/> which was paſſed in Parliament, and hear the King and both Houſes agree unto it (as in this caſe there is no Miracle to him who did not ſee it) how can you with Juſtice condemn and execute a Malefactor, who ſhall urge at the Barr that he never ſaw the Statute upon which he ſtands Indicted; nor had any knowledge or notice thereof other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe than by hear-ſay, and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of Authors and Books; which, ſince they are no ſufficient proof of Gods ſetting his Hand and Seal to a Law by Miracles, he ſees no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why they ſhould be proofs for paſſing that Statute; and conſequently, that as to him that Statute is not in force. What you would reply to one who ſhould give this for his Plea, upon ſuch an Indictment, ſuppoſe as ſaid unto your ſelf in the caſe of Miracles not ſeen by you, but reported by good Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. Laſtly, this would excuſe all Infidels who have been ſince the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles times, even thoſe that lived in their times, in caſe they ſaw
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:32708:66"/> no Miracles. But if any of you ſhall further ſay after the learned <hi>Chillingworth,</hi> That God in his Juſtice may permit ſome true Miracles to be wrought to delude Men who have forged many: I anſwer, That by this you help the Jews who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed to believe the Doctrines of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding their Miracles. For why may not they ſay; God in his Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice for our ſins might permit thoſe true Miracles to be wrought by Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt and his Apoſtles to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lude us who have forged many? I hope this Anſwer will ſatisfie any rational perſon; but if it do not, I have another anſwer to give out of Mr. <hi>Chillingworth</hi>'s own words, Pag. 144. It is impoſſible that God ſhould lye, or that the Eternal truth ſhould ſet his Hand and Seal to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of a falſhood; or of ſuch a Doctrine as is partly true and partly falſe: the Apoſtles Doctrine was thus, (<hi>viz.</hi> by Miracles) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed; therefore it was intirely true, and in no particular falſe or
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:32708:66"/> uncertain. If you reply, this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicts Mr. <hi>Chillingworth</hi>'s former poſition: I muſt anſwer, That if Mr. <hi>Chillingworth</hi> be found to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict himſelf, relying upon his own reaſon, it is not my fault, nor doth it make any thing againſt our Church.</p>
               <p n="1">1. If you will have us guilty of Sin, and Haters of God, for refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to believe on that account; it is neceſſary, according to the tenor of your own law, that the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles be done amongſt, and ſeen of, us. <hi>If I had not done amongſt them, the works which no other Man did, they had not had ſin; but now have they both ſeen and hated both me and my Father.</hi> And yet I think it is by chance indeed, if any ſay, That this Teſtimony is nothing to them, meerly becauſe they have not ſeen a Miracle; it is the Teſtimony it ſelf that they except againſt. And yet, 2. There is a difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt remaining out of Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and remaining out of ſubjecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to that you call the Holy Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:32708:67"/> Church: Suppoſe we grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the truth of theſe things, it might perhaps be a ſin to remain out of her Communion, and yet a duty to remain out of her ſubjecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Miracles, as hath been ſaid, may evince the truth of ſuch and ſuch a Church; and yet make no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all in order to the proving of her either Supreme or Infallible: though yet, miſtake me not, by Communion, I do not mean a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion total or local in all her Doctrines and polluted modes of Worſhip; but partial Spiritual in thoſe Doctrines and Performances, ſuppoſed to be confirmed by thoſe Miracles. However, 3. It is well you make it no worſe with them that refuſe to believe theſe things they have not ſeen, than to deſtroy Faith, and take away all humane converſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I was afraid you would have charged them as Chriſt did the Jews, <hi>with ſin againſt the Holy Ghoſt;</hi> though yet, as it is, your charge is ſo high, it can never be made good. For may not Faith,
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:32708:67"/> think you, evidence <hi>things not ſeen,</hi> upon the account of Divine Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, unleſs we believe what we never ſaw, upon the report of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham Hartwell</hi> and <hi>John Brerely?</hi> May not one Man believe another about worldly things with a humane Faith, unleſs one Man believe another a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Heavenly Doctrines with a Faith Divine? Or can Thieves and Traytors ever imagine, that a Law publickly promulged by the King, and practically atteſted by the whole Nation, may as warrantably be pleaded againſt by them, as the private Teſtimony of a few ignote Travellers may be excepted againſt by us, eſpecially when they diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe largely about Miracles; which, if your own Doctors ſay true, neither they, nor any Man elſe can with certainty diſtinguiſh from lying Wonders? We have notice of the Reigns and Acts of the ſeveral Kings and Queens of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> no otherwiſe than by hear-ſay, and by Authors and Books; and we have notice of the Lives and
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:32708:68"/> Acts of <hi>Beviſe</hi> of <hi>Southampton, Robin Hood,</hi> and <hi>Little John,</hi> by hear-ſay, Authors, and Books; and will any conclude the one is to be credited as well as the other, becauſe they have ſeen neither, and both come to us reported by that, you may have the forehead to call, a good Authority? Your grand Argument as is before obſerved, comes to nothing, becauſe we have not ſeen your Miracles; howbeit we give a ground for no ſuch inferences as theſe, but are ready to proportion our belief according to the worth and weight of the Teſtimony, be it Divine or humane. Nor yet will the Infidels be excuſed, for that they have not ſeen the Miracles; for in the Apoſtles time, <hi>Their ſound went into all the Earth, and their words unto the utmoſt parts of the World,</hi> Rom. 10.18. And now in theſe days, beſides the univerſal Tradition of the Church, we have reaſons and Records undeniable, to evince the truth of Chriſtianity, and of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles having been done to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:32708:68"/> it: Howbeit thoſe who have not heard at all, or heard no better proofs for the truth of Chriſtian Religion, than you bring for your Popiſh Miracles, if excuſable for not believing before; doubtleſs may yet remain in the ſame venial con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition as they were.</p>
               <p>And now for a cloſe, 4. Give me leave to mind you, 1. That in the beginning of this Epiſtle, you would have Faith deſtroyed, transformed into Fancy, Humour, and Opinion, if built on any foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation ſave Divine Revelation, or what we did certainly know to be infallibly true. And now here you will have a total deſtruction of Faith, unleſs it may be built upon the private Apocryphal reports of <hi>Abraham Hartwell, John Pory, John Brerely,</hi> and ſuch like Men, not only fallible, ſubject to errour, and in a poſſibility to be miſtaken in this very thing; but Men that cannot be concluded with any pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability of reaſon to be in a capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city to know the certain truth of
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:32708:69"/> what they ſay, they do affirm. 2. You can now preſent us with an argument from Mr. <hi>Chillingworth,</hi> ſufficient at once both to convince an Heathen of the truth of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity, and to prove the Divinity of the Scriptures. It is impoſſible that God ſhould lye, and that the Eternal Truth ſhould ſet his Hand and Seal to the confirmation of a falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, or of ſuch Doctrine as is part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly true and partly Falſe. The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles Doctrine was thus, (<hi>viz.</hi> by Miracles) confirmed: Therefore it was intirely true, and in no particular falſe or uncertain: And yet in your Diſcourſe with the Lay Gentleman, you had not a word to ſay for the truth of Chriſtianity upon Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Grounds; nor any thing for Scriptures being the Word of God, ſave that the Spirit witneſſed with your Spirit, they were ſo. 3. The Goſpel, Scripture Doctrines we preach, are like your univerſal eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſential predications, Eternal; once confirmed by Miracles in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, or their Principal, they need
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:32708:69"/> no more. This propoſition, The <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Church is infallible, has a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal mutable <hi>individuum</hi> for its ſubject, changes every Age, may change every year; and therefore ſtill ſtands in need of new miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous confirmations: inſomuch that would we give you leave to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe Miracles wrought in <hi>Bede</hi>'s time, not ſimply to confirm the Doctrine taught, but the then <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Churches infallibility in teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; yet would that make nothing at all to prove, either that the now <hi>Roman</hi> Church is infallible, or her new deviſed Doctrines certainly true. 4. The former poſition you father on Mr. <hi>Chillingworth,</hi> will be taken for your own, till ſuch time as you quote the Chapter, Section or Page, where you had it; and if then, as much may not be done for Mr. <hi>Chillingworth</hi> againſt you, as Mr. <hi>Chillingworth</hi> in the like caſe hath done for Biſhop <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher</hi> againſt <hi>Knott,</hi> we ſhall confeſs him a Man; what would you more? and fallible; and yet withal tell you,
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:32708:70"/> that his Arguments remain unan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, nay unanſwerable by your Church; nor will ſo wiſe a man's contradicting of himſelf make any thing at all againſt, but for the eſtabliſhing the Doctrine of ours, <hi>Let God be true and every Man a Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar,</hi> Rom. 3.4. <hi>Bringing into captivity every thought to the obedience of Chriſt,</hi> 2 Cor. 10.5.5. <hi>Clodius accuſat Moe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chum:</hi> You tax Mr. <hi>Chillingworth</hi> with contradicting of himſelf, and yet you are taken in that very act; you blame that learned Writer for rely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing too much upon his own reaſon, and yet you would have us build our Faith upon yours; we muſt have reaſons forſooth, without revelation, for converſion and ſubmiſſion to the ſaid Church.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="129" facs="tcp:32708:70"/>
               <head>The Six Queries anſwered.</head>
               <p>BUt yet all after this,<note place="margin">Pag. <hi>84.</hi>
                  </note> I fear ſome of you will blame me for hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing joyned with this Catholick Church, to which by Gods mercy I am united, and judge me as hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing taken the wrong way. To thoſe who ſhall remain ſo perſwaded, I make this humble requeſt, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jure them by all the Obligations of Brotherly Love, and as they have any charity for my Soul, that they will pleaſe to tell me, <hi>Firſt, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> Fear of blame argues a ſenſe of Guilt; you confeſs your having joyned with [this] Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Church, and that implies your having ſeparated from [the] Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church, the very thing your old Brethren do, and that upon juſt grounds, blame you for. And
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:32708:71"/> therefore, 2. Do not take Gods name in vain; never ſay that it was by Gods mercy, but becauſe of your own ſin and folly, that you are now divided from the commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of Chriſtians, <hi>that are all one in Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> according to <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.28. and are become united to a Sect of Papiſts, that center in nought elſe ſave three Words, which you cannot conſtrue, <hi>Roman, Catholick Church,</hi> without either Chriſtian or Holy.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> How can you but judge your ſelf to have taken a wrong way, when as you know you have left Gods way, an explicit Faith in the Lord Jeſus Chriſt; and have taken up a way of your own, <hi>viz.</hi> an implicite believing as the Church believeth? When the poor Jaylor enquired, <hi>Acts</hi> 16.31. <hi>What ſhall I do to be ſaved?</hi> Pray now, did the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle direct him to go that way you have taken, or that way you have left? Howbeit, indeed you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not rightly be ſaid to walk in that wrong way you have taken, or to
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:32708:71"/> believe as the Church believes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Church hath one manner and Rule of believing, and you ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; unleſs you'l ſay, what yet I think you will not, that the Church, like you, believes ſhe neither knows what, nor in whom, and is a Rule of believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unto her ſelf. 4. Humble re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts and Brotherly love we ſhall let alone till another time, but out of Charity to your Soul, and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs of many others, a ſolution is endeavoured to all your Quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> Whether they themſelves are certain, paſt all poſſibility of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing miſtaken, that the Chriſtian Religion is the only ſafe way to Salvation: <hi>i. e.</hi> Whether they are infallibly ſure of this point, and how come they to be ſo infallibly aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured?</p>
               <p n="1">1. It is not ſo proper to ſay, Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion, as that Chriſt is the only way to Salvation; <hi>I am the way, John.</hi> 14.6. nor need there ſhould be any addition of [ſafe] as if there were other ways to Salvation though ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:32708:72"/> dangerous: <hi>For there is no other name under Heaven given amongſt men, whereby we muſt be ſaved; neither is Salvation in any other,</hi> Act. 4.12. <hi>Bellarmins</hi> ſaying, <hi>tutiſſimum eſt,</hi> was well for a Papiſt, yet would ill be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the mouth of a Proteſtant. 2. Though we ſhall not ſay that we are certain of this point <hi>ex parte noſtri,</hi> beyond all poſſibility of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaking; for that were to make our ſelves Gods pure Acts, not men compounded <hi>ex actu &amp; potentia,</hi> of what we are, and what we may be: Yet we ſay we are aſcertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed hereof <hi>ex parte Dei,</hi> beyond all poſſibility of being miſtaken; becauſe God that cannot lie, hath declared it, and taken away the actual hurt of that miſt, that yet naturally we are ſtill prone unto. And hence, 3. Though we do not ſay that we can infallibly aſſure our ſelves, nor dare ſay that we are infallibly ſure of this or any other point; Yet we affirm that we are moſt ſure of this point, Hiſtorically, Morally, as men; ſo ſure, as the beſt Authentick Hiſtories,
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:32708:72"/> Univerſal Traditions, and the moſt rational Arguments can make us ſure, with a certainty, <hi>cui non ſubeſt dubium,</hi> excluſive of all doubt: Though yet, this notwithſtanding, as ſome do, and we may ſurmiſe, <hi>poteſt ſubeſſe falſum,</hi> there is a poſſibility of its being otherwiſe, a poſſibility of our being miſtaken.</p>
               <p n="2">2. We are aſſured hereof infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libly, ſpiritually, as Chriſtians, find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in our ſelves a faith of adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rency freely given beyond, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that of evidence by natural means to be obtained; nor will it be either reaſonable or charitable for you to call this our faith fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy: for ſith we make it out, that what we believe is true, <hi>objectivè,</hi> beyond all contradiction of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; wherefore ſhould you queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the goodneſs of the God of truth in confirming us <hi>ſubjectivè,</hi> eſpecially when we, who know our own Hearts, if not well enough, yet better than you, affirm, that from time to time we experience
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:32708:73"/> it, are ready to ſeal it with our lives, and that Ancient godly Book, called the Bible, hath many ſpeeches and promiſes of ſuch a ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> Whether they have the ſame aſſurance, and from the ſame grounds, or from what grounds, that this ſort of Chriſtianity, wherein I now wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip God, is erroneous and damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble?</p>
               <p n="1">1. We do not ſay, that ſort of Chriſtianity wherein you worſhip God, is erroneous and damnable; but that that ſort of Popery wherein you worſhip Images, invocate Saints, adore a piece of bread, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is ſo. 2. That this ſort of Popery is erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous and damnable, we are cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain from divine Scripture ground, <hi>Thou ſhalt not make to thy ſelf any gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Image,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>thou ſhalt not bow down thy ſelf unto them,</hi> Exod. 20.4, 5. <hi>When ye pray, ſay, Our Father which art in Heaven,</hi> Luk. 11.2. <hi>Thou ſhalt worſhip the Lord thy God, and him on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:32708:73"/> ſhalt thou ſerve,</hi> Matt. 4.10. <hi>In vain do ye worſhip me, teaching for do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrins the commandments of men,</hi> Mat. 15.9. 3. True it is we have the ſame grounds of aſſurance for all points of Chriſtian Religion, affirmatively, nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively, reſpect had to their Verity; and yet have we not the ſame grounds for all, reſpect had unto their Charity; and therefore may we have aſſurance for all upon the ſame grounds, yet not the ſame aſſurance. 4. The Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit is ſent in a ſpecial manner to convince the world of ſin, for not believing, and to perſwade all the Elect to believe in Jeſus Chriſt. But which, or how many other points the Holy Ghoſt will certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly give in evidence for, or againſt, I ſhall not determine.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Suppoſe I were willing upon their perſwaſions, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquiſh this way, wherein I now am; what ſort of Chriſtianity (<hi>viz.</hi> whether the way of the <hi>Lutheran</hi> or <hi>Calviniſt,</hi> of the <hi>Greeks</hi> Church, or of the <hi>Armenian,</hi> or <hi>Ethiopian,</hi> or
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:32708:74"/> whether the way of the <hi>Engliſh In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependents,</hi> or <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> or <hi>Quakers,</hi> or of the <hi>Fifth monarchy</hi>-men, or the way of the new <hi>Arrians,</hi> or <hi>Socinians,</hi> or any other, and what) ſhall I fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, and why, as the only ſecure way to ſalvation? or is it enough to ſecure my ſalvation, if I be a Chriſtian oppoſing the Roman Church, and believe, or disblieve what I pleaſe, ſo it be in contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to the Roman Church?</p>
               <p n="1">1. I can eaſily ſuppoſe you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced of the naughtineſs of the way that you are in, and yet at preſent can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſuppoſe you willing to relinquiſh it for any of thoſe ways you menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; indeed there is another way you ſeem to be thinking of, becauſe you ſay nothing of it; and had not your perfidiouſneſs been ſuch, that the Chieftains thereof will not allow you preferment, I little queſtion but they have Motives that might work upon you. 2. The way (as you call it) of the <hi>Lutherans,</hi> the way of the <hi>Calviniſts, Arminians, Engliſh
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:32708:74"/> Independents,</hi> be not ſeveral ſorts of Chriſtianity, or ſeveral ways to ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation; but ſeveral opinions held out, ſeveral forms of Government under which ſeveral Chriſtians live, that are all in the ſame ſecure way to ſalvation, <hi>viz.</hi> Jeſus Chriſt: and therefore, 3. I ſhall not perſwade you firſt or laſt, to be of any of theſe ways, but, as you ſay well, to become a Chriſtian, believe in the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and him alone for ſalvation: and then as to other points, believe, or disbelieve, not what you pleaſe, but what God in an hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble uſe of lawful means ſhall be pleaſed to make known unto you; <hi>Lord what wilt thou have me to do?</hi> Acts 9.6. And then though I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not tell which of the ways fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned you'l be for, may be for none; yet certain I am you'l ſtand up with me in contradiction to the Church of <hi>Rome:</hi> becauſe ſhe above all other Sects, ſets her ſelf moſt notoriouſly to contradict our only Lord Jeſus Chriſt; will needs ſit as God in the Temple of
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:32708:75"/> God. However, 4. ſuppoſe I were willing upon your perſwaſions to relinquiſh this way wherein I now am, what ſort of Popery (<hi>viz.</hi> whether the way of the Dominicans, Jeſuits, or Franciſcans, or the way of the <hi>French</hi> or <hi>Italian,</hi> or the way of your <hi>Thomiſts</hi> or <hi>Scotiſts,</hi> nominal or reals, or whether the way of <hi>J. S.</hi> who makes Tradition, or the way of <hi>R. E.</hi> who makes the Church the Rule of Faith, of any other and what) ſhall I follow, and why, as the only ſecure way to ſalvation? or is it enough to ſecure my Salvation, if I be a Papiſt oppoſing the Proteſtant Churches, and believe or disbelieve what the Prieſt my Confeſſor pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, ſo it be in contradiction to the Proteſtant Churches?</p>
               <p>If't be ſaid, that yet for all this you do not differ in points of Faith: We anſwer, Firſt, you differ in what is more conſiderable, the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation and Rule: <hi>J. S.</hi> and his party holding Tradition; <hi>R. E.</hi> and his party holding the Church to be
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:32708:75"/> the Rule of Faith: And then in a ſubdiviſion, the <hi>Italians</hi> holding the Pope; The <hi>French</hi> maintaining that the Council; and <hi>R. E.</hi> again that the vaſt community of all Chriſtians, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ought to be meant by the Church. Nor does it end thus; <hi>Bellarmin</hi> holds that by Miracles the Church can be proved true no more than credibly; you'l needs prove your Church by Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles to be the univerſal Judge, and the infallible Guide of Faith, and that certainly <hi>certitudine fidei,</hi> directly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to, and far enough beyond what <hi>Bellarmin</hi> ere attempted. 2. The differences betwixt the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> and the Dominicans, Whether God pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>determinate every action, Whether Election and Reprobation depend upon foreſight, be about points of Faiths, and more material than any point in Controverſie betwixt <hi>Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians, Independents,</hi> and <hi>Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts:</hi> If you ſay you agree in all points your Church has defin'd to be of Faith, it's not ſimply and una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimouſly, as you pretend to agree in all points of Faith: but in all your
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:32708:76"/> Church has defin'd or can agree that you ſhould agree in, whoſe definiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and politick Arbitration, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with your irrational forced ſubmiſſions, be nothing to us, nor to the Queſtion. However you uſe to tell us herewithal, that an agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the letter or words is worth nothing, unleſs there be an agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in ſenſe. And now you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trovert the ſenſe of almoſt all your Churches definitions.<note place="margin">Conc. Trid. Seſſ. <hi>25.</hi>
                  </note> Due Honour and veneration, ſaith your Church, muſt be given to Images, and then one ſort of you conclude the Image in it ſelf muſt not in any manner be worſhipped,<note place="margin">Bellar. de Imag. ſanct. <hi>l. 2. c. 20.</hi>
                  </note> but only the exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plar be worſhipped before the Image: Another ſort, that the ſame honour is due to the Image, as is due to the exemplar: And a third ſort, that the Images in themſelves, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly, ought to be honoured, but with a leſſer Honour than the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplar it ſelf: and if you urge yet, that you all agree the definitions to be true in the ſenſe intended by the Church her ſelf, we reply that you your
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:32708:76"/> ſelves be the Church, that thus falls out about the ſenſe, do not know what's your own meaning; and add further, that we all agree the Scriptures to be true in the ſenſe intended by God, yet will not that content you.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Whether they, who would teach me that ſort of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity to be the only Religion, wherein Salvation is to be attained, which they would have me follow and imbrace, be infallible in their teaching of this particular?</p>
               <p>We do not tell you of this or that ſort of Chriſtianity being the only Religion, wherein, but of Jeſus be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the only Chriſt, through faith, in whom Salvation is to be attained; and though we dare not ſay, that we are infallible in teaching this particular, yet are we certain that this particular which we teach is true infallibly, and that one infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble according to Chriſts own pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, <hi>Matt.</hi> 28.20. goes along with
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:32708:77"/> us in teaching thereof; your Prieſts want ſuch company, and therefore not being able their Miniſtry pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfully to evidence in mens under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings, the verity of what they ſet themſelves to Preach, they labour to ſet up an infallible viſible Authority, unto which they moſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudently aver, that all perſons muſt and ought to yield a blind obedience.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fifthly,</hi> Whether they are infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libly ſure, that all who do not follow and imbrace that fort of Chriſtianity which they would have me follow and imbrace, ſhall be damned?</p>
               <p n="1">1. You are always in hand with your ſeveral ſorts of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity, an expreſſion ill becoming one, that hath Chriſtian for his name, and Catholick for his Sir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>name, and therefore diſclaimed by us.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="143" facs="tcp:32708:77"/>2. We tell you that all thoſe that imbrace Jeſus Chriſt by Faith, and follow him in love, ſo far as ſhall be made known unto them whom we perſwade you to imbrace and follow, ſhall be certainly ſaved, and thoſe that do not, ſhall be cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly damned.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Such Sectaries as you, that make ſeveral ſorts of Chriſtianity, and maintain it to be neceſſary to Salvation, in all things to obey and follow this or that ſort of Chriſtianity, do certainly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve for that very thing to be eternally damned: But what God will do either with you or them, leſt herein we ſhould be like you, I ſhall not determine.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sixthly,</hi> Suppoſing that they are not infallible in theſe particulars, whether will it not rationally, and neceſſarily follow, that poſſibly I may at preſent be in the right way, and they in an errour; and if ſo,
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:32708:78"/> what reaſon can they give, why I ſhould forſake my preſent Guide, whom I believe to be infallible, to follow them who confeſs they may be, and therefore, for ought they know, are at preſent miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in what they believe and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> If we neither did, nor could bring any other proof for theſe particulars, ſave our own Teſtimony (fallibility on our part ſuppoſed) it would rationally and neceſſarily follow <hi>quoad nos,</hi> that poſſibly at leaſt you might be in the right way, and we in an er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour: Though yet, <hi>quoad rem ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſam,</hi> the ſequel, this notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, be impoſſible, becauſe theſe particulars might be in themſelves infallibly true, and we neither know, nor be able to evince it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> You may ſtrongly ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, but if your own principles abide firm, you cannot, do not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that the Roman Church your
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:32708:78"/> preſent Guide is infallible: For Faith, according to you, is an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible aſſent of the underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſubmitting it ſelf obediently to the revelations of God: And therefore ſith you have no reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of God for, but one expreſs againſt, the infallibility of the Roman Church, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.22. Your own definition will tell you, it is impoſſible that your underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſhould exert an Act of Faith about it; nor yet, ſuppoſe you had divine Revelation for it, or that God himſelf ſhould ſay to you, the Roman Church is infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible, were you ere the nearer. For it's poſſible you may com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit an errour, nay err in your underſtanding of thoſe words; and conſequently your underſtanding ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver give an infallible aſſent to that which God intended by them. Howbeit,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> We can tell you as for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly, that <hi>à poſſe ad eſſe non va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let Argumentum:</hi> it follows not, we
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:32708:79"/> may be, therefore we are; or we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs we may be, therefore for ought we know at preſent, we are mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for though we ſtill confeſs we may be miſtaken in what we believe and practiſe, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect had to our deſert, and natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral proneneſs, yet do we know that God of his mercy, through the Miniſtery of his word, hath at preſent fully ſatisfied us, that as to the main we are not; and if in ſome things we differ and wander, yet doubt we not but God for Chriſts ſake, will pardon our errours, as well as our other ſins, and cauſe us to keep the unity of the Spirt in the bond of peace, <hi>Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs whereto we have already at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, let us walk by the ſame Rule, let us mind the ſame things.</hi> Phil. 3.16. However,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> We do not deſire you to forſake your preſent Guide and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low us; but to forſake your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Guide, us, and your own ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſh humour, and follow the Lord
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:32708:79"/> Jeſus Chriſt. You pretend and would have us to believe the Romiſh Church to be infallible independently on the Scriptures, becauſe God by Miracles, as you imagine, has confirmed it ſo to be; and ſith ſo, we would have you at leaſt allow us to believe Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Doctrines, confeſſedly ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed independently on that Church, or elſe excuſe your ſelf from being an Heretick, ſith you'l believe, nay, preſs others to believe one propoſition, and refuſe another equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly propoſed at your own account: Not may this be retorted upon us either by Mr. <hi>Johnſon</hi> or you. For,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> Though we own all the gifts Chriſt gave unto Men <hi>for the perfecting of the Saints, and work of the Miniſtry,</hi> according to <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.11, 12. yet do we neither claim nor admit of ſuch a propounding Authority, as you without any divine warrant pretend unto.<note place="margin">Pag. <hi>9.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="148" facs="tcp:32708:80"/> 2. Though your Church equally impoſe all her Tenets, reſpect had to her own uſurped power; yet does ſhe not equally propoſe all, reſpect had to the evidencing of their truth. For ſome ſhe propoſes as Divine, but does not prove them ſo to be, as her Doctrines about the real Preſence, and Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory:<note place="margin">Pag. <hi>81.</hi>
                  </note> others ſhe not only pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes as ſuch, but evidently e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces them to be Divinely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed; as the Doctrine of the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and the Incarnation: to theſe we aſſent, thoſe we except againſt as not ſufficiently repreſented to us: And yet ſay,</p>
               <p n="3">3. That two propoſitions may be equally propoſed to, and not equally work upon the underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: preaching the Goſpel to the Gentiles, and preaching the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel to the <hi>Jews,</hi> were both pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed with equal evidence and Authority, <hi>Go ye into all the world, and preach the Goſpel unto every Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi>
                  <pb n="149" facs="tcp:32708:80"/> Mark 16.15. and yet did <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> with a thouſand others believe that, and disbelive this without any crime of Hereſie, if of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice or inadvertency imputed to them.</p>
               <p>If there be any who hath any value for the Authority of the great S. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> I ſhall beſeech them to read this following Text of that Saint, and to conſider whether I have not in my pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings obſerved his Rule and Method; and let them but change the word <hi>Manichaeus</hi> into <hi>John Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin,</hi> and how nearly it will concern them.</p>
               <p>S. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> againſt the Epiſtle of <hi>Manichaeus,</hi> which they call funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental, <hi>cap.</hi> 5. <hi>edit. Pariſ. Tom.</hi> 61.46. If thou ſhalt find any one who doth not as yet believe the Goſpel, what wilt thou do when he ſhall ſay unto thee, I do not believe? But neither had I believed the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel,
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:32708:81"/> unleſs I had been thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to moved by the Authority of the Catholick Church: Thoſe therefore to whom I ſubmitted, when they required me to believe the Goſpel, why ſhould I not alſo yield obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence unto them, when they direct me not to believe <hi>Manichaeus?</hi> Take your choice; if you tell me I muſt believe the Catholicks, they give me advice not to give cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit to you; and therefore if I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve them I cannot but refuſe to believe you. If you tell me I muſt not believe the Catholicks; you proceed ill, when you go about by the Goſpel to perſwade me to believe <hi>Manichaeus,</hi> becauſe it was from the Preachings of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks, that I believe the Goſpel it ſelf. If you tell me I did well when I believed the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks praiſing the Goſpel, but I do ill when I believe the ſame per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons decrying <hi>Manichaeus,</hi> do you take me to be ſo ſtupid as with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any reaſon given unto me I ſhould believe or disbelieve what
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:32708:81"/> you pleaſe? <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But if you have any Reaſon to offer unto me, lay aſide the Goſpel; if you hold your ſelf to the Goſpel, I ſhall adhere to thoſe upon whoſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands I believe the Goſpel, and ſo long as I obey them I ſhall not believe you. But if by accident you ſhould find any thing in the Goſpel moſt evidently touching the Apoſtleſhip of <hi>Manichaeus,</hi> you will weaken the Authority of the Catholicks in my eſteem, who require me not to believe you; but that being weakened I ſhall not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the Goſpel, becauſe I believe that by them: ſo that whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver you bring from the Goſpel will be of no force with me. Wherefore if nothing be found in the Goſpel for the manifeſtation of <hi>Manichaeus</hi> his Apoſtleſhip, I ſhall rather give credit to Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks than you. But if any thing ſhall be there found manifeſt on the behalf of <hi>Manichaeus,</hi> I ſhall neither believe them nor you: Not them, becauſe they told me a lie
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:32708:82"/> of you; nor ſhall I believe you, becauſe you urge that Scripture to me, which I believe upon their Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, who told me a lie in rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to you, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> may be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered either as a Witneſs acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us, what the Church then held, or as a Doctour rationally de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing and proving of concluſions: had you quoted him under the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer notion, I ſhould not have queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned the truth of any thing that Great <hi>Auguſtine</hi> had ſaid, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out undeniable evidence to the contrary. But ſith you cite him as Doctor, I ſhall value S. <hi>Auſtins</hi> Authority, as S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> had learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to value the Authority of other pious learned Doctors of, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his time, not credit what he ſaith, becauſe he ſaith it, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he proves it true, either by Canonical Authorities or probable Reaſons. Howbeit,</p>
               <p n="2">2. You obſerve the Rule and
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:32708:82"/> Method not of Saint <hi>Auſtin,</hi> but Mr. <hi>Knot,</hi> ſubſtituting <hi>John Calvin,</hi> for <hi>Mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaeus;</hi> and I might by the ſame Rule obſerve the Method of Mr. <hi>Chillingworth,</hi> ſubſtitute <hi>Arians,</hi> as great pretenders then, as the Papiſts are now, for the Catholick Church; put <hi>Goth</hi> or <hi>Vandal</hi> converted by them for S. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> for <hi>Manichaeus</hi> write <hi>Homouſians,</hi> and then try whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Argument, if but firſt fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to your purpoſe, be not, as he ſays, like a buskin that will fit any leg: but I ſhall wave this, and in a juſt parallel let you ſee plainly how far different your pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings are from thoſe of the great S. <hi>Auſtin.</hi> Firſt then S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſpeaks of an Infidel that did not as yet believe the Goſpel; you direct your ſpeech to Chriſtians, Proteſtants, that do already believe it, and that up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the account of Univerſal Traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the Scriptures, and the Divine Atteſtations of Miracles, far bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter grounds than your Popiſh prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples can or will allow. Secondly, S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſuppoſes ſuch a one to
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:32708:83"/> come and ſay I do not believe, and thereupon ſeeks to bring him to, and eſtabliſh him in the faith: you deal with ſuch as ſay they do believe, and ſeek to overturn their faith eſtabliſhed as aforeſaid, aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring it's no better than fancy and an humour: thus did not <hi>Auſtin.</hi> Thirdly, S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſpeaks in the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular number, and preter Tenſe, Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther had I believed the Goſpel, unleſs I had been thereunto mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by the Authority of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church: You ſpeak in the plural and preſent Tenſe, we muſt not, do not, believe the Goſpel, unleſs our Faith be found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon the Authority and infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libility of that ſociety of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, which is in Communion with, and in ſubjection to the Biſhop of <hi>Rome.</hi> Fourthly, thoſe to whom <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſubmitted, required him to believe the Goſpel and disbelieve <hi>Manichaeus,</hi> who held two firſt Principles, and conſequently two Gods, and maintained ſeveral other er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous apparently repugnant there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto:
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:32708:83"/> thoſe to whom you have ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, require you to believe the Real preſence, Purgatory. Image-worſhip, with other ſuch like Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane inventions, and disbelieve <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin,</hi> who teacheth the Goſpel, and declares againſt all ſuch Doctrins as do not accord therewith. Fifthly, We do not adviſe you to believe the Romaniſts, nor did you at the firſt believe the Goſpel by the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniſts Preaching, but by the preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Proteſtants: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if you'l adhere to thoſe upon whoſe grounds you did at firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the Goſpel, ſo long as you o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey them, you ſhall not believe the Romaniſts; and if they ſay (what one would think they ſhould) you did well when you believed the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants preaching of the Goſpel, but do ill when you believe the ſame perſons decrying the Romaniſts, are you ſo ſtupid as without any reaſon given unto you, to believe or disbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve what they pleaſe? <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Had you indeed been bred a Papiſt, and then could have proved the Papiſts
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:32708:84"/> the only Catholicks, and Proteſtants as groſs Hereticks as the <hi>Manichees,</hi> there might have been ſome ground for your parallel with S. <hi>Auſtin;</hi> as it is, you proceed upon a three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold diſadvantage and diſparity.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:32708:84"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
